I see somebody come up behind me, they can see, I'm trying to park, they can move over, no,
they come right up behind me, go on the horn, and you know, you immediately feel
just an immediate anger response, right? Well, after the ice bath, it's flat. So there was an
immediate automatic down regulation of my autonomic emotional response to a psychological
stressor, somebody honking at me, that was trained and generalized from the ice bath.
There's an experiment of one, I'm not claiming this as a published study, but so I think there's
a direct autonomic training component as well, in terms of the strength and the automaticity,
the ease with which you can regulate emotions, that they can become kind of automatically
regulated. You don't have to overthink it, it becomes smooth and effortless to some extent,
and that's the place where you want to get. Hey everyone, to celebrate the launch of my
new book entitled Protocols, I'm pleased to share that I'll be hosting three live events
very soon. The first live event is in New York City at Radio City Music Hall on September 17th.
The second event is in Los Angeles at the Dolby Theater on October 8th. And the third live event
is in San Francisco at the Masonic on October 28th. At each of these events, I'll be discussing
topics from the book, and my favorite part, taking questions directly from you, the audience.
To get tickets, you can go to hubermanlab.com slash events and use the code protocols to
get early access. Again, that's hubermanlab.com slash events and use the code protocols to get
early access to tickets. Welcome to the Huberman Lab podcast, where we discuss science and science-based
tools for everyday life. I'm Andrew Huberman, and I'm a professor of neurobiology and ophthalmology
at Stanford School of Medicine. My guest today is Dr. Ralph Adolfs. Dr. Ralph Adolfs
is a professor of psychology, neuroscience, and biology at Caltech University, and a world expert
in the neurobiology of emotions. Today, we discuss what emotions are, how they grow and shrink in our
brain and body, and why some emotions seem to recruit our behavior and decision-making, and some
simply don't. We also discuss where and how emotions are mapped in the body, and we dispel common myths
about the brain-body storage of emotions from our past, which is a very commonly discussed topic
that, frankly, as you'll learn today, many, if not most people, get wrong. We also discuss why some
people are able to observe, but not react to their emotions, and what tools may assist in helping you
build better emotion regulation. As you'll soon realize, Dr. Adolfs is uniquely positioned to explain
the real neuroscience and psychology of emotions, and how to put that information to use. Today's
conversation, therefore, ought to be valuable for people of every age and profession, and for anyone
interested in improving their emotional life and understanding of others. And now for my conversation
with Dr. Ralph Adolfs. Dr. Ralph Adolfs, welcome. Thank you, Andrew. Pleasure to be here. Longtime
admirer of your work, because you're one of the few people who has studied these things we call
emotions, brain states, cognition, and much more in humans. There have been others in the field of
neuroscience, of course, but I would argue few people have combined a real grounding in neural circuits
with an interest in what most people think of as a psychological set of issues in a way that also
takes into account the animal data and really the broadest picture of this thing that we call
emotions. I'm just going to start with a statement of gratitude. Thank you for doing that, because it's
so easy for people to stimulate a brain area, see an animal or a human behave or speak in a certain
way and say, oh, this is the brain region for this. And you've long been pushing back on that.
It's a tall order, you know, and one impetus for the work that I've been doing in the book that I
co-wrote with David Anderson, the book that I have forthcoming with Princeton University Press
is precisely to do what you just said, is to kind of integrate and pull together
findings and emotion from animal studies, findings from social psychology. Typically,
those people in those fields don't talk to one another. They do very different studies,
very different methodologies. And so trying to integrate across disciplines that are that far
apart to really try and get a get a sense for what are emotions in a sense that would satisfy
psychologists and lay people about human emotions. But they would also speak to the mechanisms that
you can study in mice, for example, or flies, as David Anderson does.
So how do you think about emotions and how do they relate to brain and bodily states?
The basic answer is that I think of emotions as functional states of a particular type. They
should be understood by what they do, their function, rather than how they happen to be
constituted in the human brain or differently in an octopus nervous system or in an AI, which
we should talk about. And so the way to situate them is to think of control of behavior in response
to particular types of environmental challenges. So at the sort of simplest level,
you'd have reflexes, you know, I put my hand out on a hot stove, or you tap the patellar tendon on my
knee. And there's like a very rigid behavior that's adaptive, that's very rigid. But just for that
particular circumstance, I withdraw my hand, that's a reflex. At the opposite end, you would have,
you know, goal directed, general volition and planning, everything, you know, the stuff we do all
the time, that's extremely flexible. And so if you have a bear or a tiger, you know, something
charging at you, that challenge requires a control of behavior that's intermediate between
those two extremes. I can't have a reflex for a bear if it's far away, or if it's close, or if it's a
rattlesnake, or a tiger, or all the different kinds of potential threats out there. Instead, I need
something that's more flexible, which emotions are. So that's the sort of big picture, that emotions are
functional states that have particular features or operating characteristics for dealing with
certain types of environmental challenges, like running away from a bear. I mean, first of all,
I think the question, what is an emotion, is a good and a valid question. It's not an ill-posed
question. You occasionally run into the view that, well, emotions don't really exist, or we don't
really, you can't really say anything about them. The question is just ill-posed or meaningless. I don't
think that's the case. Paul Griffith's philosopher wrote a book some years ago, I think 97 or so,
what emotions really are, where he first kind of made the claim that, well, they don't really exist,
you know, and you could see how people come to that conclusion. If you survey all the different
theories that are out there, Joe Ledoux, or Lisa Feldman Barrett, or Paul Ekman, they look pretty
different. And so you might come away with the impression, look, even the experts can't agree on what
emotions are. The words we have for emotions predate modern science. So it's just a confused
concept. I don't think that's the case. I think, I mean, there's room for revision, but I think everybody
kind of knows what emotions are. And I think it deserves a straight answer that science should
provide. I think the question is well-posed enough to admit of an answer. And then how could you start
getting to an answer? So let's just start sort of from the simplest case would be to list some
examples. So you could say, well, you know, emotions are anger, fear, disgust. You could list specific
examples that are uncontentious, I would hope, where pretty much everybody agrees, okay, these are examples
of emotions, right? You could do the same if I asked you, what's a car, right? And you would say, well, you know,
it's a Mercedes and a Honda and a Toyota, or if I asked you, what's a bird? And you would say it's a
robin and a hummingbird and an eagle. So you could list examples. That's not an answer yet. What you
would then want to say is, well, what is it in virtue of which these examples, what makes them all
instances of an emotion? What do fear, anger, et cetera, share in common? What features do they have
that makes them emotions? Just like what the cars or the bird species have in common, that makes them
cars or birds. And so David Anderson and I did that in our book a decade ago or so, now the
neuroscience of emotion, where we listed some features of emotions that helps to answer the
question and sort of get a handle on what is it that these all share in common. I elaborate on that
and have a longer list and really go into detail and, okay, so what are the features of emotions
in my forthcoming book? Maybe I'll just list a couple to go through them quickly. So one feature of
emotions is priority, which is that they can take over your behavior. That they share in common with
reflexes. If I put my head on a hot stove, you know, I can't help but withdraw it. And if you're suddenly
confronted by the bear, you can't help but run away or crawl into a ball or whatever your adaptive
behavior is. So they have priority and interrupt your behavior, which is something that the Nobel laureate
is that Herbert Simon already pointed out in a paper back in the 50s or 60s, that they're interrupt
mechanisms of a certain kind. If you're just going about your business and normal goal-directed behavior,
you always need to be monitoring for the bear or the tiger, the predator that's out there.
And if you detect that, emotions have to take over or you're dead. So priority is sort of one.
That doesn't distinguish emotions from reflexes or fixed action patterns. They share that.
Another one is valence that psychologists ubiquitously mention, which is sort of the
simplest dimension along which you can organize emotions in terms of their similarity. So anger,
disgust, fear, you might see are more similar to one another than either of those, as would say,
happiness. There's some similarity structure, some emotions cluster together, some are further apart.
And the simplest dimension, which is one that Charles Darwin already mentioned in his book,
the expression of the emotion in men and animals, they called it the principle of antithesis,
is valence, which is approach or avoid, pleasant or unpleasant, this basic valence dimension.
Are there any neutral emotions? I ask this because your colleague at Caltech, who I
respect tremendously, Marcus Meister, once wrote a review where he said, you know, a good way to think
about sensory systems and maybe neural systems of all kinds is that they're encoding for yum,
yuck, or meh. And the meh is a very interesting one, just like an animal or including us can go
forward, backward, or stay put. Now we can go side to side too. Of course, those are just different
versions of forward in this context. And I sometimes wonder, because algorithms are repurposed
across different neural systems, if there is indeed a meh emotion, or maybe the emotion is meh.
I don't want to take us down a philosophical path, but does that make sense? Because as long as we're
talking about valence, anger and happiness, clearly, you know, sad and happy, okay, opposite
ends of the spectrum. But what it was, apathy? Is there a state of prioritization of doing nothing?
It's a really good question. I mean, I think, you know, when you list these features,
like priority, valence, I'll get to some others. One question is, which of these are necessary?
You know, like a package of all of these features that emotions have, do you need all of them? Or
are some of them sufficient? And I think the answer is some of them are sufficient, but there's some
that are necessary. I think priority is necessary. I think valence, maybe not, as you were alluding to,
I could imagine there's still valence, but it's at a neutral region of the spectrum. But then there's
other ones, which are the ones that David Anderson has studied in particular in the hypothalamus in
mice. And I think goes into great detail in the podcast that you had with them, which are scalability
and temporal persistence. And so scalability would be that an emotion can scale in intensity. One of
the best examples of that has been, is for the case of fear and the bear coming at you. So typically it
would scale from anxiety and monitoring, you know, there's the bear sort of out there, to fear, where you
might run away or hide, to panic. So that's a threat imminence scalability. And that's something where emotions
are different now from reflexes, because reflexes are binary. It's all or nothing. I'd rather pull my hand away or
nothing. The knee jerks are not. It's not, there's not like some scalable package in there. And then temporal
persistence is even more something that's essential to emotions and speaks to their function, which is you have this
internal state, let's say of aggression or a fear that has to last some time, because the bear might be
around for some time. So you might be running away, or you might be attacking in anger, those are phasic
little bouts, but the actual internal state that is motivating those persists for quite a long time. So
temporal persistence is really important. And it allows the person or the animal to incorporate lots and
lots of information that's coming in, and to have a motivational state that would be suited for that
kind of environmental challenge. It's not like a hot plate, where if you pull your hand away, you're
done. The bear is out there, and it might come back, it might still be lurking in the forest. So you
better be afraid for some period of time. David Anderson studied this a lot in terms of what neural
circuits, what properties of neurotransmitters in the brain could actually implement persistence,
where you have really slow neurotransmitters like neuropeptides, for instance, which is what he
studied. But my colleagues at the University of Iowa actually did a really cool study in humans that
showed the temporal persistence of emotions independent of memory. So here's a study. They took
patients with amnesia, so these were like four or five people who had medial temporal lobe, hippocampal
damage. They live in a time window of maybe a minute or so. I used to study these patients when I first
started as a postdoc at the University of Iowa with with Damasio. And you know, you can talk to them,
they can process information. But if you go to the toilet, and you come back five minutes later,
they would stand up and shake your hand, introduce themselves to you, because they would have no
recollection of having met you before. So just no memory, very strong anterograde amnesia, as it's
called. So they had those and controls. They showed them really sad movie clips in all cases.
The patients can understand and watch the movie clip, they get really sad and weepy.
Right after watching these sad movie clips, everybody rates, how sad do you feel? The
amnesia patients feel really sad. The controls feel really sad. You wait five minutes. You then
ask the controls, well, how do you, how sad do you feel? And they say, yeah, I still feel a little bit
of sad, sadness in me, because I remember having seen the movie. And if you ask them, why do you feel
sad? They say, well, because you showed me the sad movie five minutes ago. The amnesia patients,
you ask, how do you feel? They say, I feel really sad. And I don't know why. I have no idea. And you
ask them, do you remember seeing a movie? They say, nope. There's like no declarative memory of the
movie, but there's still the temporal persistence of the sadness. It lasts some time. So I thought this
was a really cool study, because it showed very clearly that there is temporal persistence in
emotions. And sadness probably has one of the longest time constants, as we know from personal
experience. But it's separate from just declarative memory. It's not that you're remembering that the
bear is there. That's going on too. But independently of that, the emotion state has its own temporal
persistence. The state has to last some time. And again, that's something that reflexes don't have.
It just goes straight through. There's no temporal persistence.
I'd like to take a quick break and acknowledge our sponsor, Helix Sleep. Helix Sleep makes mattresses
and pillows that are customized to your unique sleep needs. Now, I've spoken many times before on
this and on other podcasts about the fact that getting a great night's sleep is the foundation
of mental health, physical health, and performance. When we aren't getting great sleep on a consistent
basis, everything suffers. And when we are sleeping well and enough, our mental health, physical health,
and performance in all endeavors improve markedly. Now, the mattress you sleep on makes a huge
difference in the quality of sleep that you get each night. How soft it is or how firm it is,
all play into your comfort and need to be tailored to your unique sleep needs.
If you go to the Helix website, you can take a brief two-minute quiz and it will ask you
questions such as, do you sleep on your back, your side, or your stomach? Maybe you know,
maybe you don't. Do you tend to run hot or cold during the night? Things of that sort.
You answer those questions and Helix will match you to the ideal mattress for you.
For me, that turned out to be the Dusk mattress. I've been sleeping on a Dusk mattress for more than
four years now, and it's been far and away the best sleep that I've ever had. If you'd like to
try Helix, you can go to helixsleep.com slash Huberman, take that two-minute sleep quiz, and
Helix will match you to a mattress that's customized for you. Right now, Helix is giving
up to 27% off their entire site. Helix has also teamed up with TruMed, which allows you to use your
HSA, FSA dollars to shop Helix's award-winning mattresses. Again, that's helixsleep.com slash
Huberman to get up to 27% off. Today's episode is also brought to us by Rora. Rora makes what I
believe are the best water filters on the market. It's an unfortunate reality, but tap water often
contains contaminants that negatively impact our health. In fact, a 2020 study by the Environmental
Working Group estimated that more than 200 million Americans are exposed to PFAS chemicals,
also known as forever chemicals, through drinking of tap water. These forever chemicals are linked to
serious health issues, such as hormone disruption, gut microbiome disruption, fertility issues, and
many other health problems. The Environmental Working Group has also shown that over 122 million
Americans drink tap water with high levels of chemicals known to cause cancer. It's for all
these reasons that I'm thrilled to have Rora as a sponsor of this podcast. I've been using the Rora
countertop system for almost a year now. Rora's filtration technology removes harmful substances,
including endocrine disruptors and disinfection byproducts, while preserving beneficial minerals
like magnesium and calcium. It requires no installation or plumbing. It's built from medical-grade
stainless steel, and its sleek design fits beautifully on your countertop. In fact, I consider it a welcome
addition to my kitchen. It looks great, and the water is delicious. If you'd like to try Rora,
you can go to rora.com slash Huberman and get an exclusive discount. Again, that's Rora,
R-O-R-R-A dot com slash Huberman. It is striking to me that maybe 30 years ago or so, there was
discussion about whether animals have emotions. Based on these criteria, priority, valence,
scalability, and persistence, is it generally agreed upon that animals have emotions? I believe they do
because I love my dog and other animals, and I want to believe that. But as scientists, if we step back,
do they meet the criteria for emotions that you're setting up here for us?
Absolutely. Yes. So if you have those criteria, those functional criteria, and you would add one
or two others, many states in animals, and certainly the states that we would ordinarily interpret
as emotions in our pets, in our dogs, cats. By the way, I loved your dog.
Oh, stronger.
In the waiting room there.
Yeah, he's just hanging out.
They would meet those criteria, and they would have functional emotions. We should talk more about
this. There's also the claim now from Anthropic that large language models have functional emotions
as well. That's so wild. We have to return to that because I think it kind of boggles the mind.
You know, how could a machine have emotions?
Right. Well, but again, these are functionally defined emotions, and I think there's no problem
assigning to AI to some extent and certainly to many animals those functional emotions. Where it gets
complicated is that in us, and also by assumption in animals, I have no doubt, they also have conscious
experiences of emotions. And most people take the conscious experience of the emotion as the ground
truth for the emotion. Emotions without conscious experiences of emotions sound like an oxymoron.
It's like you can't have that. The conscious experience is the emotion, which is what William James
said, which is what Joe Ledoux says. And I think it's implicitly there across essentially every
psychological theory is the assumption that emotions really are types of conscious experiences, which I
think is the intuition that if I ask you, how do you know what's the ground truth, right? How do you know
you're having an emotion? You would say, because it's a certain type of conscious experience because of how it
feels. And if I asked you more specifically, how do you know it's sadness versus anger versus fear? You
would say because of how they feel. They feel different. And so we take the conscious experience,
our own introspective access to the conscious experience as the ground truth. That has a lot
of problems associated with it, deep philosophical problems. But just practically, it has two big
problems that I think science should avoid. One is it gets really problematic to know whether or not
animals have emotions because we don't know how to test whether or not they have conscious
experiences. I have no doubt that they do. It's just that there's no scientific way to test currently. So we
should have different criteria. And the other question is, if you tie emotion to the conscious
experience of emotion, that is you equate, you conflate emotions with feelings, well, then you're not
studying emotions, you're studying consciousness. We spoke about Christoph Koch earlier, great respect for
people that are studying consciousness, but I don't want to study consciousness. That's too hard. And there's lots and lots of
debates and disagreements. So if we can avoid that and study emotions in the absence of needing to
study conscious experiences of emotions, we can move forward with the science, which is what every other
discipline does. So if you're a vision researcher, right? So you study vision, you study consciousness.
Oh, you know, you don't need to. I mean, you can, but there's a huge amount of work that people do
studying vision and how that works in the brain, studying memory, you know, any other cognitive
process without needing to study conscious experiences. They're typically accompanied in
humans. And if you, if you talk to the lay person on the street and just say, I'm a vision researcher,
they take you to be studying the conscious experience of seeing, perhaps. Or if you say,
I'm a memory researcher, they take you to be studying the conscious experience of recollection.
But scientifically, most people working in those fields don't study consciousness. And it's perfectly
valid to study vision and memory, you know, in horseshoe crabs or the plesia, where nobody has
any claims about consciousness. We should do the same thing with emotion. And then we can have an
integrated science across species that can move forward without needing to tackle the difficult
problem of consciousness. Again, yes, for sure, we and other animals have conscious experiences of
emotions. And that's very important. But we also have conscious experiences of seeing and memory.
As a scientific discipline, we should separate the conscious experience from the process,
from the emotion. And that's the way we make progress. That's the one of the main arguments that
David and I had in our book and that I reiterate in the forthcoming book.
David At risk of taking us in a philosophical direction, I'd like to actually ask a
biological, psychological question. Given these criteria, you know, priority, valence, scalability,
and persistence, but really focusing mainly on priority, I think all of us have had the experience
of an emotion coming on, but not in its kind of overtaking maximal form. Like, okay, we feel ourselves
getting annoyed, and we can observe the emotion growing. The arousal state is familiar to us,
we understand. Let's assume in this example that we understand why it's happening. Maybe you're in
line at the store, and the person ahead of you is taking everybody's time by doing something that's
really unnecessary and kind of obnoxious to us in that moment. And so our frustration is rising,
and we are observing the emotion, even though the emotion is us, right? It's within us. And then at
some point, we might blurt something out, or we might feel compelled that we have to just say,
excuse me, like, could this maybe be taken care of some control?
But you have some control, and there's this almost like running together of two consciousnesses.
Like, there's like two of us in there at the same time, observing self, observing the outside world,
and then at some point, the prioritization gets to the point where, like, we just do something.
And sometimes it's a decision, and sometimes it overtakes us. Now, at the opposite extreme,
we've all observed, and you can just go on X, the social media platform, and for some reason,
the algorithm likes to serve up a lot of examples of people like on planes losing it,
people going unhinged, like, you know, I like people just like completely melting down,
and it's very, in our language, hypothalamic, right? And so people are drawn to that.
I have an antidote to those people. They should take ice baths. I can tell you more.
Oh, well, listen.
They should take ice baths. I think this helps, seriously.
Yeah, well, ice baths, yeah, let's definitely talk about ice baths, and ultra,
ultra races, because you're training for one.
No, but I think what you said is exactly right, and extremely important for humans, and probably
unique to humans as opposed to other animals, which is that we can be conscious of and monitor our own
emotions, and by doing so, we can regulate them to some extent. So emotion regulation and control,
and monitoring emotion, being aware of what emotion you have, those two go hand in hand. And your Stanford
colleague, you know, James Gross spawned this huge field in the 90s, I guess, when it started, of
emotion regulation that is now huge. I just finished my term as co-editor of this journal, Affect of
Science, and I would say about a quarter or so, or a third of the submissions are about emotion
regulation. It is so important in humans, and most of pathologies and difficulties about emotions are not
about the emotion per se, it's about our ability or disability to control them, to regulate them.
If you don't mind, because of your understanding of emotions and states and neuroscience,
but also your experience as a human in the world, has anything you've learned changed the way that
you watch your emotions grow, decide when to step in, when not to step in? You don't seem like an
impulsive person, so we're not, but most people aren't, we're not talking about pathology here,
and I'll seed this question by saying, you know, I have a few friends who were in tier one special
operations, and you know, that's high-risk, high-consequence work. We've had Alex Honnold
on the podcast, high-risk, high-consequence endeavors, and they all say the same thing,
which are that emotions cloud logical judgment. So they're somehow far from emotions, or their
emotions don't get prioritized. But of course, these are the, all of these people that come to mind
have, you know, healthy marriages, now, you know, healthy families, they're loving people,
they have anger, they have emotions, but they sort of categorized emotions as cloud judgment in the
professional or, you know, peak performance context. Therefore, they don't allow them to be
prioritized. Sounds a little bit robotic, sounds a little bit mechanical, quote-unquote, on the
spectrum. People like will say these things, right? But in some ways, provided they're allowed to
allow themselves to be emotional and let emotions, quote-unquote, take over in the right context,
that's kind of the ideal circumstance, right? Yeah. So what do you know that allowed, that has
impacted the way that you think about emotion regulation that perhaps people could consider,
if not benefit from? Yeah, I think it's, you know, it's a mixture. On the one hand,
you absolutely need emotions. If you have no emotions, as we know from Antonio Damasio's original
work in his book Descartes' Error, which he put out just as I was starting as a postdoc in Iowa in 1994,
I think, you know, if you have massive frontal lobe lesions that make it the case that you're no longer
emotionally responding to stimuli, the consequences are devastating, which is that you cannot
make decisions, complex decisions in your life, you can't organize your life, you're not motivated
to take the right path through life, because you don't feel one way or the other about the different
options that are available. So it's clear that not having emotions is very bad. And certainly if
you're out facing the bear, which may not happen to too many people these days, that would be very
bad. On the other hand, being able to regulate them and control them is definitely a human skill
that's very important, and that helps you a lot. The first part is what you were talking about first
earlier, which is the ability to monitor your emotions, to identify your emotions. I think Lisa
Feldman Barrett actually first did the main work on this. It's a topic called emotional granularity.
It's like how fine a grain can you conceptualize and be aware of your own emotions. And then once
you're aware of them, you can bring various emotion regulation strategies, mostly cognitive reappraisal
type of strategies to bear on the emotion and thereby, to some extent, control your emotions.
How important is it to use language to provide that granularity? I've certainly experienced
like feeling a bunch of things around a particular scenario. And if you can't separate out the elements,
it can feel overwhelming. People always say, if you can name the emotion, but I find that a little
tricky because sometimes it's not one emotion. It's a bunch of things. It's confusion. It's frustration.
Are those the same thing? I don't know. And I think many people, myself included, sometimes it just feels
too much, not because the emotion is so big, but because it's such a tangled jungle of where there
isn't really language to disentangle it. Absolutely. Yeah. I don't think you need to
put it into language. And I think people's strategies vary. Some people think in words,
some people think in pictures. Most people are a mixture. And if you look at different languages,
you know, if you're French or German speaking like me, bilingual, we have different words for different
emotions, but you need some sense of the concept, which I think the concepts for emotions are pretty
much universal across languages. So, you know, there are all these different examples of emotion
words from different languages, like schadenfreude is one that people know now, you know, joy at another
person's misfortune from the German. Giegel, I think is often trumpeted as another example. I forget
what the culture is, but this is the emotion you feel if something is just unbearably cute. There's a
great book. Tiffany Watts Smith has a book, I think it's called The Book of Human Emotions, which is
basically like a little dictionary, an entry from A to Z of all the different emotion words in different
languages. But the fact that we don't have a word for Giegel or for schadenfreude in English,
you perfectly well have the concept. I just described it to you. You have no problem understanding
what the emotion is. And so I think as long as you have some kind, some concept which need not be put
into words, some way to think about and differentiate the different emotions that are going on in you,
that gives you a purchase on your ability to, to some extent, evaluate them and say,
this is an emotion I want, or this is an emotion that I don't want, and then to act on it through
various strategies, cognitive reappraisal, for example, or acceptance, depending on what your
strategy is. Yeah, the psychologists seem to disagree here because many people, some in on this
podcast, all of whom are experts will say, you know, if you don't allow yourself to feel the emotion,
then it grows. And other people will say, well, if you focus on something, then it grows. And this is
where I think neuroscience can be of great help, because probably both things are true. And it
depends on the context. But yeah, that's exactly right. Maybe this is a good opportunity to talk
about sort of dynamic attractor states, which is, and I don't throw out that language to confuse
people. But there is this idea in neuroscience, right? Like if we, you and I both, you know, talk
about this cup, and I slide it forward, and then we start looking at it, and more and more brain,
brain circuits are going to be devoted to we could spend several hours, it's not a very interesting
conversation. But we if we do that about an emotion, we feel because of something somebody
said to us at work or online, I think we're all familiar with the idea that we can go down these
rabbit holes within our own mind. Absolutely. And it's a very dangerous way to live.
Just knowing that it exists, perhaps can be helpful. Yeah, because it's almost like if you go
far enough down a path, it's like a horror movie, if you go far enough down a path, it's very hard to
extract. Absolutely, absolutely. I think I mean, cognitive reappraisal or any other sort of complex
re-appraisal strategy for emotions. It is a double edged sword, and it's trainable. It's as you say,
if I really focus on okay, now, you know, I'm starting to feel sad, I really don't want to feel
sad, I really don't want to feel sad, I really don't want to feel sad. Well, the more I think
about it, the sadder I get, right? Or same with anxiety, some emotions are probably more prone to
going down this rabbit hole than others. But again, it's a trainable skill that there are other ways
of dealing with it where you can kind of just stop that process from going down at all. You want to stop it at
the earliest front end. I mean, one quick answer to the question of what's the most successful
strategy is the earlier you can stop that process, the better. And so in the first place, don't get
yourself into a situation where you're going to be anxious, or guilty, or sad, or whatever emotion
you want to avoid. So situational avoidance, just in terms of structuring your environment,
would be one strategy. And then once you're in it, I think it's idiosyncratic to a large extent,
so you would have to figure out what works for you. But it's definitely trainable.
Two parts are trainable. One is the specific strategy, so you can do cognitive reappraisal
without overthinking it and going down the rabbit hole and actually feeling the emotion even more.
And the other one is just the strength and automaticity of control that you have,
which brings me to the ice bath. Shall I briefly talk about the ice bath?
Because this is relevant, actually. So I started doing these a while back. One of my former colleagues,
Justin Feinstein, who now runs a float clinic on Maui. I forget how it came about, but we were talking
about floating ice baths. And he mentioned you, and he mentioned Wim Hof. I said, you know, take a look
at these guys. And I saw, you know, Wim swimming in some frozen lake. It looked kind of interesting.
Anyway, so I started doing ice baths some time ago. They weren't that popular yet back then.
And now my wife bought an Amazon, like a horse-watering trough or some big thing, insulated it.
Yep. It's a lot safer than being out on a lake too.
Pretty on the porch. We'll talk about that.
And I get, you know, these 40-pound ice bags every week. They know me very well at Joe's Ice
up there. Every time I go in, they say, hey, boss, having a good party again tonight, eh?
I'm like, yep. I can eat a lot of ice. But so this is the interesting thing. When I start first week,
it is terrible, super painful. You know, you go in, it's like a whole-body cold-pressor task,
right? Second week, it's also, you know, your breathing goes up, your heart rate goes up.
But gradually, and kind of with some automaticity to it, now I go into the ice bath immediately.
My heart rate goes down. My breathing goes down. I get super relaxed. So this is the interesting
part there, apropos of emotion regulation. It generalizes for me. This is an experiment of
one. But for me, it generalizes. So previously, prior to the ice bath, driving around Pasadena,
and I don't know, in the last year or two, this seems to have risen somehow. I'm trying to park
on the street. There's a lane next to me. I have my signal out. There's a parking space. It's clear
what I'm trying to do. I see somebody come up behind me. They can see. I'm trying to park. They
can move over. No. They come right up behind me, go on the horn. And, you know, you immediately feel
just an immediate anger response, right? Well, after the ice bath, it's flat. So there was an
immediate automatic down-regulation of my autonomic emotional response to a psychological stressor,
somebody honking at me, that was trained and generalized from the ice bath. It's an experiment
of one. I'm not claiming this as a published study. But so I think there's a direct autonomic
training component as well in terms of the strength and the automaticity, the ease with which
you can regulate emotions, that they can become kind of automatically regulated. You don't have to
overthink it. It becomes smooth and effortless to some extent. And that's the place where you want to get.
I've known Wim a long time. And although I sometimes, in my opinion, unfairly get tacked to the
deliberate cold exposure, as we call it, thing a little too much, because we talk about many things
on this podcast, not just that, I do find it very useful. And years ago, my lab had collaborations
with a special operations community. And they'll tell you that one of the reasons it's such a wonderful
tool is it's so reliable. You always get an increase in adrenaline, norepinephrine in the brain,
and to some extent, and this might surprise you, perhaps not, you get often reductions in cortisol,
which is kind of paradoxical. But when people practice it, it's very reliable and provided
it's not so cold, or it's an open lake where you can-
It's reliable and super efficient.
And safe. I mean-
Unless you're doing it in a lake, or you're doing hyperventilation.
Five minutes after a shower, it's extremely efficient.
Yeah, that's a lot. That's good.
Well, after five minutes, you can look at my body mass index. After five minutes,
I get hypothermic, so I can't stay in very long.
That's a good long while and even in a cold shower. And there is now evidence of improved
resilience to subsequent stressors of the sort that you described. And there are some okay papers.
I think it's a wonderful tool, especially for this buffering, this immediate stress or anger
response. Very powerful. Before we went on, Mike, we were talking about a different type of stressor,
which is the ultra marathons that you're currently training for, a hundred mile race, which is,
by the way, super impressive, even just to shoot for it. I know you've done others.
I'm trying, it's an operative word here.
Okay. Well, I have confidence in you.
Talk to me in two months.
Yes, I will. I have confidence in you. You're going to finish this hundred mile race.
But we were talking about something that I think is relevant to bring up now, which is
you were describing how, you know, at some points during these races, you just feel like complete
garbage, but then you start to feel better. And so then the next time you feel like complete garbage,
you have the cognitive knowledge that you felt terrible, then better again. And so you're
starting to integrate over longer periods of time. So here's another example of emotion regulation,
but over much longer time scales. It's a little bit harder to access for most people than a cold
shower.
No, but I think this is one thing, one reason, there are many reasons, but there's one reason that I
love these ultra marathons and sort of identify as an ultra runner, even though I didn't do it for
decades. And I'm just now getting back into it because of that nonlinearity. You have these major
ups and downs and, you know, sort of mantra that ultra running has co-opted is, you know, relentless
forward momentum. But the sort of psychological equivalent is just relentless optimism, like
optimism in the face of adversity. You have to just keep that mindset. And everybody there is like
that. You know, you come around like mile 40, mile 50, mile 60, you come around some curve,
and you look and feel like crap. People go, looking good. Nobody says, well, looks like you're
not going to make it. No, nobody says that, right? So everybody is super positive. You're hanging in
there and it is really hard. And you know, you've just been going downhill, your knees are shot,
you have blisters, you've been vomiting, super tired, and you extrapolate and you think this is not
going to work. But if you refuse to give up, doesn't always work, but about half the time or so,
it levels out and it starts going back up again. You keep going. I mean, you feel wrecked at mile
50. I feel wrecked or earlier, mile 30. And so trying to think forward and say, well,
we have to do this over again. This is like not fathomable. So it's a really interesting exercise
in not giving up and being able to do something that you think is impossible to do. For that matter,
all of your listeners would think it's impossible. If any of your listeners went running with me,
they would conclude two things. One is they're faster than I am. And two, I'm not going to be
able to do 100 miles, which means if I actually finished the 100 miles, all of you would be able
to do so as well, which I think is true. I think anybody can do it. Anybody who's basically healthy,
if they only wanted to, which is the key, could actually do it. So it's just a really
interesting exercise. You know, it's only 30 hours. Well, only, but it's only 30 hours. It's not like,
you know, years. How hard can it be? How bad? Well, it's hard, but it's doable. It's definitely
doable. And so it's just in that sweet spot of something that seems impossible and is just
unbelievably hard, but doable. And that's attractive somehow, if you can do it, which,
of course, doesn't happen all the time. Yeah. And I don't know if there are any data on this,
but for people that have lived through really hard things and come out better,
or have pushed themselves to deliberately do hard things of the sort that you're describing,
I do think that the memory of that can recall our body and brain's ability to lean into other hard
things. I think so. I mean, it must be the case. I don't know of any good experiments on that,
but you know, was that post-traumatic resilience, I guess they call it, you know? I mean,
some people come out of very difficult circumstances. Yeah. Maybe they do,
quote unquote, the work they need to or not. And, and they just say, okay, like I'm better for life
because I'm out of it. Other people carry the wounds of that forward in a way that they're,
you know, they're psychological and sometimes their physical health is a downward trajectory.
It's a very interesting thing about like, how do, how should we conceptualize pain and pain ending?
Like some people seem to live in the discomfort of the pain having even happened.
Yeah. You can certainly persevere and overcome, you know, severe adversity if it's time limited.
And I think just your own sort of belief in yourself and your capability to overcome adversity,
as you were saying, is one important component. Another one is something like gratitude or awe.
And you get to appreciate and just value, you know, just the fact that I'm here talking to you. I mean,
I'm just, I'm actually grateful and feeling some sense of awe right now at just existing. And so
getting to that point where you're just, every morning you wake up and you have this sense of,
I guess, gratitude and awe or some combination of those emotions. I think that's a really valuable
thing to carry out of all of this. And, you know, it takes time to kind of accumulate,
but I like living that way.
I want to get back to the emotion system, but I'll just, I feel inclined to mention we had Dacher
Keltner on the podcast.
Oh yeah. Well, he's worked on awe.
On awe and he defined it so beautifully. He said, it's when we bring our attention from
a small spatial scale to a large spatial scale, or from large to small. But then during the course
of our discussion, he added that this is also true in the time domain. So when we live our life day
to day, we start to feel kind of lost in time and awe becomes less common. But when perhaps
we run a hundred mile race across 30 hours, we realize how much can happen in 30 hours.
One could say, oh, well then you finish the race and the rest of life seems trivial.
But it seems the opposite is true, that we realize that time is this very elastic thing,
at least in our minds. And all of a sudden we have awe for the fact that we have so many days of life
to live forward. It's very interesting. And it almost speaks to the ice bath again. Like you have
this very compressed, stressful experience that gives you that gap, that gap between stimulus and
response that seems very hard to access unless we subject ourselves to these kinds of things.
No, and I think that capability, the, I mean, people think, you know, chimpanzees maybe can feel awe,
but I think it's, I think it's a uniquely, at least as we have it, it's uniquely human emotion.
And it's based on a broad sort of meta cognitive ability we have, which is to detach our conscious
experience from the here and now and do like mental time travel. It's pretty derivative to
the need to understand other people. So I could put myself into your shoes right now. I can do that.
I could imagine sitting where you're sitting and I'm seeing Ralph Adolph's here. You know,
I could imagine zooming around and adopting another person's perspective in space. We certainly zoom
around in time and reminisce, you know, stuff from the past, imagine things in the future. And I think awe
is like that too. We adopt a different perspective that's not just tied to the here and now, which I
think is probably a crucial ability that distinguishes the nature of conscious experience in humans,
which is that we have some control over it. I can simulate what it's like to be you. I can imagine
being in the past or in the future. I can zoom out broadly when I'm feeling awe. And I think animals
are more just stuck with whatever the senses are delivering to them right now. That's the content of
their conscious experience. We can use it flexibly. And that's, I think, why we can plan and write
novels and fiction and think about most of the time, right? If I ask you, what's in your consciousness?
What are you thinking about? It's not stuff that's in front of you. You're daydreaming. You're like all
kinds of places. And that really gives the human mind the power that distinguishes it from any other
animals. And it's the reason we have everything that we have that makes us so different. So awe,
I think, is an example of a uniquely human emotion that derives from that ability to adopt a vast point
of view or a point of view that's not tied to just whatever the senses are delivering to you.
I'd like to take a quick break and acknowledge our sponsor, AG1. I'm excited to share that AG1 has just
launched their newest formulation, AG1 Pro. AG1 Pro takes the clinically-backed AG1 formula,
which is a blend of vitamins, minerals, probiotics, and adaptogens, and adds three
important new ingredients, creatine monohydrate, calcium HMB, and zinc carnosine. Each serving has
five grams of creatine monohydrate to support muscle strength and performance, as well as brain health,
calcium HMB to support muscle recovery and reduce muscle breakdown, and zinc carnosine to support and
improve the lining of your gut. All three of these ingredients have compelling science to support them,
and therefore, I love seeing them added to the existing AG1 formula. As most of you know,
I've been taking AG1 every day for nearly 14 years now. I started taking it long before I even knew what
a podcast was. It's a great product, and it's now made even better with the new AG1 Pro formula.
If you would like to try AG1 Pro, you can go to drinkag1.com slash Huberman to get a special offer.
AG1 is giving away a free bottle of omega-3 coenzyme Q10 with your first subscription.
Again, go to drinkag1.com slash Huberman to get a free bottle of omega-3 coenzyme Q10 with your first AG1 subscription.
As long as we're talking about assessing the emotions or the perspective of another,
what are some favorite experiments, either yours or others in the field, about perception and assessment of emotions?
You know, I've seen a number of studies like, oh, you know, people with lesions here or there see scary faces.
It's not that scary. What's the sort of general conclusions about those studies now in 2026?
Because I have a feeling a lot of what was in the textbooks when I was a graduate student may not still hold up.
When I started as a postdoc in the early 90s with Damasio, I started my career on that topic
by studying this famous patient, SM, who had selective bilateral amygdala lesions,
and the finding was that she's unable to perceive fear in emotional facial expressions.
Perceive fear? Could she feel fear?
Subsequently, we also did that. It took, for some reason, because it's just harder to do,
it took some years. Justin Feinstein, who has the float clinic in Maui, was the first author on that paper.
So some years later, we took that same patient to haunted houses. We took her to an exotic pet store
where there were snakes and spiders. We showed her horror movies, a whole bunch of things,
and found also she doesn't seem to consciously experience fear either. So there seemed to be this
very specific deficit for fear tied to the amygdala from one patient. So that's a big caveat. Does this
generalize? Well, yes, the amygdala is important for fear, but just saying it's a center for fear is
overly simplistic. It's embedded in a big network of structures. There's individual differences,
and so on and so forth. The perception of emotions has been studied a lot and probably has been
the topic of the most acrimonious debates to some extent. So Paul Ekman, back in the 70s,
famous... By the way, I dedicate my forthcoming book to him because he probably had the biggest
impact on modern emotion science of any single person. But his claim to fame was he went to New
Guinea and, you know, these non-Western cultures and claimed that universally across all cultures,
people recognize these so-called basic emotions from facial expressions. If you Google this now,
you know, emotional facial expressions, you will find pictures of emotional facial expressions. Lots of
AI companies and computer algorithms are predicated on the idea that you can read out the emotion from
somebody's facial expression. He had six of them. Happiness, surprise, fear, anger, disgust, and sadness,
sometimes contempt added in there. Well, it turns out it's more complicated than that. And actually,
Lisa Feldman Barrett, of all people, co-authored a paper with me and three other people a couple of
years back that the title was something like emotional facial expressions reconsidered. We took stock of the
whole literature and asked, is this really true? Is Ekman's claim really true? Can you tell how someone
feels from their facial expression? And the answer is, well, not nearly as well as you would think,
and in general, not. And the reasons are methodological. And once you think about it,
they make a lot of sense, which is that the emotional facial expressions that Ekman pioneered,
I used them in the first 1994 Nature paper with his amygdala lesion patient,
those aren't actually what you normally see walking around the world. People don't have those facial
expressions. They are posed facial expressions by actors. Yeah, they're very extreme. And then the
task is like, well, here's a list of emotion words, happiness, fear, anger, disgust, et cetera. Pick
the one that matches the face. That's the typical task. So it's multiple choice. Look, if I gave you
a bunch of emoticons and a bunch of emotion words and asked you to match them, you could do that very
easily. It wouldn't show you anything about emotions. It shows you that there's, by convention,
there's some association between these things and these things. That's it. So when you actually see
real world facial expressions, and when instead of giving a list, you just ask people, just generate
freely a word that describes that, you get something that's much, has much more variation,
much more heterogeneity, which then was part of the ingredient for Lisa's whole claim that variation
is the norm and that in fact, emotions are in some sense constructed rather than packages to be
found in nature, which I disagree with that part. But the emotional facial expressions for the
perception of emotions in others and in animals, I was just talking before coming in here to one of
your colleagues about your cute dog. And they've done studies, there's several studies now where dog
owners, if you ask them, can you tell if your dog feels guilty when you come home because it did
something bad? Dog owners are pretty convinced they can tell. Well, if you do a controlled experiment,
they're a chance. They think they can tell. So our conviction that we can tell something about
people or animals, their very emotion states, just from looking at the facial expressions,
our conviction vastly outstrips our accuracy. We're pretty convinced we can do it. We're mostly not
so accurate, which makes sense because ordinarily, it's not the, it's not just some facial,
you know, if I see you now and you look sad, I wouldn't stop there and I would say,
Andrew Huberman is sad. I would ask you, how are you feeling? What's going on? I would probe you
and get a lot more information. Maybe you would say, oh no, I'm just this drink I had tasted bad or
something, you know, that caused me to make a certain facial expression. So in general, these artificial
lab situations where all you see is a picture of a face and asked for the emotion, we don't do that
in the real world anyway. We would probe further, we would take into account the whole
circumstances, we would ask the person and then you can disambiguate these emotions. So it's not
that we cannot tell what emotions people or animals feel, but we don't do so normally just from a single
slice like a facial expression. I feel like at least in the context of romantic partnership,
so much more of our assessment of another person and their assessment of us is actually a
mathematical integration of noticing when frequency of speech or frequency of text
is heading in a negative direction relative to the mean, right? At a particular time of day.
And I think the brain is really good at saying like, like normally somebody is pretty communicative in
the morning, but less at night for sake of example. But suddenly they're like a little more terse with
us in the morning, but maybe not even harshness. There's just fewer words exchange. And then
the brain doesn't think, oh, like they looked angry or they looked frustrated. They, you know,
like they were like, it's a little, little quieter this morning than usual. And then if it's a very
quiet person, you have, you have fewer data points to work from, but we become exquisitely tuned to this.
Absolutely. Much more than like, oh, they're, they're carrying their shoulders differently.
At the extremes, I think we see this. Somebody walks in the door and you can tell like,
they're sad, they're defeated. In general, we're looking for change.
You're looking for change. It's a time series.
And the number of times, or even just like if you probably had this experience,
like in an email with a colleague, let's move it to a different domain. There's a certain kind
of language that's used in an email that's different than the usual language. Like they've
never really used these words before. You don't even identify which words those are. Years ago,
there was this chart that some graduate student or postdoc put out that if the director of a lab
signs off with their name, it means one thing. If they punctuate their email, it means like,
let's meet, you know, like you're in trouble. You know, if there's just a dash with a first initial,
you know, there's all this, and you kind of, I laughed too. And then you realize you go, wow,
like they're really paying attention to all these subtle cues, but those seem like the kind of cues
that we rely on much more than, than like, do they look sad? Do they sound happy? And I think we
vastly underestimate this. I don't know if there are any good studies of this, but this feels like the
more relevant in the real world. No, absolutely. Yeah, we just finished a study like this where
people texted. That's all they had, but it's dynamic. It's a conversation. There's like a whole
transcript. And then the question is, what can you tell about a person, both in terms of their stable
personality and their current mood, just from that text? It turns out you can tell a lot. So people
did the study recently where people generated, I think it's about a page or so of sort of diary type
written text and asked just large language models like GPT or Claude to analyze that text without
knowing anything else and just tell me the personality profile. And it's as good as the ground truth
or as another person or a clinician would be. As good as a clinician? It gets close to the ground truth
and it's as good as like a good friend or a person who knows the person. So if you score the big five,
which is what they did in that study, extraversion, conscientiousness, neuroticism, et cetera,
you can tell that. AI can tell that just from a transcript of text quite well. So the information
is there clearly in what we say, what we write and the order in which that progresses, that tells a lot
about a person, enough that AI can basically diagnose your personality from just text. It's almost like
our brain is very attuned to when we don't get what we were expecting to get in terms of the amount
of interaction. Like I have some people that clean up the graffiti on the street where I live and
there's always an exchange of hello or like hi if one of us is on a call or busy. And I can say with
certainty because this happened the other day that if I looked over and the person saw me and then
turned away, even though we, I don't know their name. Well, maybe I do now, but that there's very
little familiarity except with we always acknowledge the other's presence. If they were to do that,
I would think, gosh, like this person's like maybe upset. That's one of the key ingredients
of Lisa Feldman-Bertz thinking, certainly in recent years, which is prediction, that most of the
information comes from when there's a mismatch between what you're predicting about a circumstance
and something that's just different, because that carries information. Something changed, right?
Like what you were saying. And Lisa's work, Lisa's thinking on emotions incorporates prediction in a
big way these days, that there's something that you're predicting about the world, but suddenly,
you know, there's a tiger or something unexpected, and you need to incorporate that, and that carries
important information. But absolutely, we're always predicting and we're taking into account things
that change, like the facial expressions, you know, the original studies, like the ones I started
doing as a postdoc, where you just show these static Paul Ekman pictures of facial affect. Well,
we never see that in people. It's always dynamic, the face is changing. And so Philip Shins, Rachel Jack,
colleagues in Scotland, for instance, have studied this in great detail, and used dynamic actual videos
of people making faces, and asked, at what point does the brain start to represent different emotions,
depending on not how the face looks, but how the face is changing.
Interesting.
So the dynamics are everywhere. It's super important.
Because when we look at babies, and they start to smile for the first time, or they express what we
think is, you know, humor, or something like that, we are so tuned to faces, because they can't really
do much, and whether or not they're interacting with us or not, is really dependent on our behavior.
There's a lot of control there. We're putting them in front of us. As they develop more autonomy,
then these sorts of dynamics really emerge.
And the face, I mean, the face is visible. And the face, the human face has way more muscles
and control than other animals do. Great apes have similar sets of muscles. But monkeys or your dog,
you can't make those kinds of faces.
Yeah, he side eyes me every once in a while. And I project onto him what that's about. But
he's a real sweetie. I had another bulldog mutt, they're both mutts, who is much, much more coarse,
less affectionate. This one is like pure butter. But of course, I don't know what's going on in his head.
He could be thinking like, this guy's the biggest jerk in the world. You know, like, I wish he'd be
walking right now. This patient, SM, who had bilateral amygdala lesions, could she experience
autonomic arousal? Could she experience stress? Could she experience anxiety under any conditions?
She could. And that's really important. So you might think that, you know, it's just like the whole
emotion system is gone. You just sort of denervated the entire autonomic nervous system. And
that's why you don't have emotions. But it's much more specific than that,
and fits with thinking about emotions as evolved functional modules for dealing with particular
types of statistically recurring environmental challenges that share some challenging feature
in common. So she doesn't have fear to external stressors, like we went with her into a haunted house,
she poked the monsters and wanted to touch things. Same with the snakes and spiders in the pet store.
But we did a study, again, Justin Feinstein, I think was the first author on this one as well,
with her and with a couple, two, maybe two or three patients who had similar lesions in collaboration
with Renee Herleman from Germany, where we put a mask on them and had them inhale carbon dioxide.
If you do that, you get a panic attack in about half the population because it makes you feel like
you're suffocating. So as soon as you get that carbon dioxide in, it changes the pH in your blood
that's detected by the brain. And you get this massive air hunger, like you suddenly can't breathe.
That's what your brain goes into this alarm mode of some suffocation, like a panic. And she and
the other amygdala patients had a full-blown panic attack when they inhaled the carbon dioxide. So
this interoceptive signal seems not to depend on the amygdala and to depend on other brainstem circuits.
So we had a very important association between different types of fear, which is, I think, a
bottom line story for the way that the science is informing our folk psychology, which is these
categories we have like anger or fear or disgust. There are many varieties. It's much more finely
differentiated than that once you look at the science and once you look at the brain systems.
They're distinct brain systems in this instance for fear to something out there in the world
versus panic of something happening inside you, like having a heart attack or not getting enough air.
I see. Maybe we could talk a little bit about the bodily representation of these things we're
calling emotions. Years ago, I posted on social media a picture of a figure from your paper with,
from your book, excuse me, with David Anderson, which was describing a study where people
self-described, so it's purely subjective reporting as I recall, where in their body they felt different
emotions. So it's kind of like a heat map in the forehead for certain emotions and in the whole body
for others. And there were a wide range of emotions. And admittedly, it's subjective report,
but does this hold up? Like, I think to myself, like, where do I feel sadness, like heartache? Well,
I tend to feel it around my heart, but maybe that's because it's called heartache. Where do I feel anger?
Well, extreme anger I'm going to feel is a whole body experience. Same thing with awe. So what,
if anything, is important about the regularity and or the variation in kind of where in our body
we feel emotions? Some people would say this is like their whole experience of life. They feel
things in their body all the time. Some people feel, I think, are more cerebral. They kind of think
things more than they feel things. You know, I think it's a great, it's a great question. I mean,
that figure that you're alluding to came from a paper, I think, in PNAS by Lauri Neumannma and
colleagues in Finland. And he and his colleague, Haini Sarimaki, they've done some of the great,
great recent studies also on experience of emotions in humans using functional MRI. But what you mentioned,
so the experiment is I just give you a word, right? I'm not actually making you feel the emotion. I'm
asking you sadness. Draw, you know, where on the body you think you would feel that emotion.
So if you think about it, it's certainly not about actual physiological changes in the body.
Nothing's measured in the body. They don't have electrons on the body or whatever. There's people
just drawing on a little mannequin where they think they would feel the emotion. It's also not
about conscious experiences of emotion. I'm not making, I'm not showing you sad movie clips or anything
like that. I'm giving you a word, a single word. So it's about concepts. It's about where in the body
people's concept of sadness or happiness or fear, where that corresponds to changes in the body.
Now, that's an interesting question, but you have to narrow it down to that,
which is a fundamental problem with most emotions, including that one. I think the title,
I forget what the title is, but it's something like bodily maps of emotions or bodily maps of
subjective experience, maybe even. It should be something like people's concept of where in the
body emotion words are associated with changes or something like that. What's interesting about that
study is that Lowry has gone on to look at it in different cultures. He's looked at it developmentally
across children and asked how these concepts and where in the body would feel emotion develop. So it's
super interesting work, but it's ultimately about people's concepts of how emotions correspond to
changes in the body, not the real actual changes in the body. But then, as you were saying, of course,
there are real changes in the body when you really feel an emotion as well. And that's harder to study,
but people have studied it quite a bit with a focus on the part of the brain that gets a lot of input
from the body, which is a part of cortex called the insula. And so there's lots and lots of work on the
insula. It gets input from all the organs in your body, everywhere in your body. So, you know, from your
heart, from your liver, from your kidney. I had a kidney stone not too long ago. We should talk about
the kidney. Have you had a kidney stone? Don't. It's really interesting. You have to pass it. Eventually,
it's passed, but it evokes very interesting adaptive behaviors. Well, just as an aside,
before I forget it. So normally for pain, extra receptive pain, like we were talking about the hot
plate before, you know, you pull your hand away or there's some kind of reflex. For the kidney stone,
that's not adaptive. There's nothing to pull away. So my wife, this was in Switzerland. We're in a
remote little town in the middle of the night. My wife sees me curled up into a ball, right, on the
floor, just kind of breathing loudly and kind of curled up and making rocking motions. And goes,
what's wrong? And I tell her, well, I have a kidney stone. And then she asked me, can't you just
stop that behavior? Or can we get on a plane and fly to the US so you can get ultrasound, maybe get
treated for the kidney stone? Can you stop curling up into a ball and, you know, making rocking motions?
And I was kind of thinking about that through my haze of pain and said, well, no, it's kind of like
the hot plate and pulling away. It's a really strongly motivated behavior to just kind of withdraw,
basically. So it was a very interesting adaptive behavior. And she called, you know,
the equivalent of 911. And in the middle of the guy of the night, some guy came down
and, you know, put a bunch of opiates into me. And he kept having the scale of, you know, on a scale
from zero to 10, how painful is it? And I would sort of go from 10 to 9.5. And it was extremely painful.
But eventually, they got me to our clinic there. I passed the stone. And it was an interesting
experience. I mean, it's pain, but just like what we were talking about for emotions, pain is not pain.
If you have a pain in your eye, or you have a pain from a hot stove, this is a very different type of
pain. And one that's, I would say worse than the hot stove. It's like, because you can't escape when
you can't rub it, you can't do anything except curl up into a ball and pray. I mean, it was horrible.
At any rate, so at that moment, had I been in an MRI study, my insula would have been strongly
activated. So this, you know, this is a region of the brain that according to theorists, but Craig was
the first Antonio Damasio as theories in a similar vein, this would be the substrate for the conscious
experience of the emotion or of pain in your body. So it's getting all this input from your body,
and representing the changes in your body as a conscious experience. This was the original theory
that William James had back in 1884, he wrote this paper in mind, what is an emotion. And his theory was
that you see the bear, you run away, your heart rate goes up, and then you feel the emotion,
which is a consequence of you perceiving all the changes in your body that happened first.
Now that's, I think, the conscious experience of emotion, yes. And a lot of that depends on
representing, perceiving everything that changes in our body. But to my mind, that leaves the question
of what the emotion is, that's still antecedent to that. You first have to trigger all the changes
in your body and run away. What's doing that? That's the emotion. The conscious experience may
well come later and unfold over some time. But the emotion state, separate from the conscious
experience, as I've emphasized, would be the one that actually motivates all the behaviors and all
the different changes in your body. So long answer to your question, there's these two
different ways of talking about the role of the body. The one that you alluded to in this figure from
Laurie Numenma and colleagues that we reproduced in her book is about people's concepts of emotions,
and they're certainly tied to changes in the body. Whether or not those are accurate, I think we just
don't know. So is it the case that those drawings that they have in the figure that we were speaking
about, if you put electrodes on your measured blood flow changes, that's actually where things change
when you have awe or anger? I think we just don't know. I think that's a set of studies that remains to be
done. But then in addition, there is the fact that all of the changes in your body are represented in
your brain in the insula. And that seems to be a big part of the substrate for feeling the emotion,
for the conscious experience of the emotion, and other things, nausea, pain, kidney stones. So it's
not limited to emotions. But the strong feelings that we have, like you have a tightness in your chest,
if you're feeling really sad, for example, that would be represented in your insula.
Because in Eastern medicine, there's strong beliefs about different organs being associated
with different emotional states, even like gall, you know, someone has a lot of gall,
the gallbladder, you know. But then again, I always have to remind people that a key feature
of schizophrenia and psychosis of other kinds is clang associations, two words sound alike,
and people link them. And so we also are subject to this in a much milder way in the world of health
and science, and especially in the public discourse. People will say, oh, you know,
a walnut looks like a brain. Walnuts are good for your brain. Well, they have some fatty acids that
are probably good for neurons, but it has absolutely nothing to do with the shape of the walnut. It's
amazing how these ideas can kind of perpetuate. Well, and I think there is some truth to them.
I think it just has, the honest answer is it has not been tested. So if you ask someone like Lisa Feldman
Barrett has made this point repeatedly, that there really is no systematic association between
specific emotions and specific changes in your body. Well, if you look at those studies,
people put a few electrodes on and they measure, you know, heart rate changes, blood pressure changes,
etc. It is extremely crude. You're looking at a tiny, tiny slice of what's going on in your body.
What you would want to do is have a detailed high dimensional readout of, okay, your gallbladder
and your liver and your kidney and your heart and changes all over your body and look at that
and ask, is there some kind of association between specific emotion states and changes,
some kind of complex change in your body. And I would bet that there is, but we just don't have
those data yet. So those studies remain to be done. Yeah, they really should be done because I could
make up a story where if someone or an animal feels extreme anger, like of the sort that they would have
right before they were in a fight, that certain immune organs would deploy a bunch of things that
prepare for wound healing or prepare for resilience in the aftermath. That just stands to reason.
Of course, I have no data for that. Well, and the link between the brain and the body,
I mean, we now understand that that is so detailed and so intricate that really brain and body are very,
very tightly coupled. And we do know that there are signatures that are distributed,
they're complicated. But Lisa Feldman-Baird herself in collaboration with Tor Weger has published
neuroimaging studies showing that for basic emotions like anger and fear and sadness and so on,
there are reliable signatures of brain activation. They're distributed, they're spread out,
they're complicated, they're not just like in one place. But given that, given that association
between emotions and patterns of the brain and the fact that the brain and the body are so intimately
tied together, I think it's a completely reasonable hypothesis that you would find a similar high
dimensional signature of changes throughout your body that are systematically associated with certain
types of emotions. I had a thought spring to mind based on our earlier discussion from the perspective
of media and advertising. It makes perfect sense why all media and advertising is incentivized to get
you to prioritize an emotion to the point where it takes over behavior. To go click and buy something
or to vote a certain way or to hate a certain group or to like a certain group. And so really
what they're fighting for is this prioritization thing. Like the path to behavior is through the
prioritization of emotion. It's basically an attentional capture. It captures your attention,
which is what emotions are designed to do. And once you've captured people's attention,
you have a captive audience and you can control them much more. And in some sense, it's obvious,
right? You get people emotional, they're more likely to behave in a certain way versus another.
But I think we underestimate the extent to which all day long we are bombarded with these signals.
Like subtle advertising doesn't really work well. Yeah. Someone said, I don't know who said it,
but you know, all A-B testing leads to like, you know, sex or violence. Because if you really just
look at what's likely to grab people's attention, you know, eventually you regress into the
hypothalamus, the more primitive states like inspire more attention, which tells you a lot about the
world, you know, and there, and there are ethical lines and there, there are societal lines where,
where you say, no, no, that's, that's too extreme, too much violence, too much skin. But it's all veering
in the, like toward the hypothalamus, so to speak. It's all getting more and more primitive.
There's a lot of processing that goes on in all these subcortical structures and certainly what we
understand best in terms of emotions are all these subcortical circuits. And a lot of that is below the
radar of our conscious awareness. I'd like to take a quick break and acknowledge our sponsor,
Function. Function provides over 160 advanced lab tests to give you a clear snapshot of your
bodily health. This snapshot gives you insights into your heart health, your hormone health,
autoimmune function, nutrient levels, and much more. They've also recently added access to advanced
MRI and CT scans. Function not only provides testing of over 160 biomarkers key to your physical and mental
health. It also analyzes these results and provides recommendations for improving your health from
top doctors. For example, in a recent test with Function, I learned that some of my blood lipids
were slightly out of range. As a result, I decided to start supplementing with natokinase, which can
naturally help reduce LDL cholesterol. And it did. In a follow-up test, I could confirm that this
strategy worked. My blood lipids are now back exactly where I want them. Comprehensive lab testing of the
sort that Function offers is just so important for health. I mean, how else are you going to know
what's going on under the hood? And while I've been doing blood work for years, it used to be time
consuming, complicated, and expensive. In fact, I used to spend thousands of dollars per year trying
to get this kind of data. And the data, frankly, were not all that good. But now with Function,
it's extremely easy and affordable. A Function membership is only a dollar a day, $365 a year. And if you think
about the information it provides and the health challenges it helps you avoid and the proactive
things that it can do for you to enhance your health, I truly look at it as a savings. To learn
more, visit functionhealth.com slash Huberman and use the code Huberman for a $50 credit towards your
membership. Again, that's functionhealth.com slash Huberman. At the opposite extreme, what happens
when I go to like the MoMA and I see a piece of art that just for some reason makes me feel a certain
way, maybe sadness, maybe happiness. Do you think that art of that sort is able to capture the circuitry
related to particular emotions across people? So not just about my unique experience. And art is
subjective, right? So there's things related to taste, but let's assume this is abstract art. So
there's no apparent faces or animals or no depictions of scenes, but let's say out of 100
people, you know, more than half say, yeah, I look at that and I just feel peace. Is it the case that
some art can tap into neural circuits or some music can tap into neural circuits that's independent of
the lyrics? I mean, we don't have the brain imaging presumably, but there is a kind of a more
sophisticated example. We're not regressing to the hypothalamus. Absolutely. But this is the stuff
that like the richness of life is also about that. Sure. And so the interesting question is which
particular features in the music or in the abstract art is it that are driving those generalizable
emotion responses? And they're certainly there. One of the earliest studies on emotion actually
was done by Anne Blood and Robert Zatori in the mid nineties or something. I believe using,
I'm pretty sure using positron emission tomography PET rather than fMRI at the time. And what they did was
they played music to people. And I think they set it up so that you and I could hear the same piece
of music. In your case, the music really does something for you. And the particular measure was,
does it send shivers down your spine? Do you get like chills, goosebumps from listening to the music?
And it does that for you, but not for me. And in your case, the same auditory stimulus,
different emotion. And from the imaging, they showed that the insula, the structure we're just
talking about the amygdala, several of these emotion related structures are indeed activated
when you have shivers, chills down your spine, listening to music. For abstract art, my Caltech
colleague, John O'Doherty had a paper a little while ago, where again, he found something generalizable.
He decomposed abstract art into the constituents or visual features that you can feed it into a neural
network and get a representation of all the different shades and colors and the basic visual
composition, basic visual features that constitute that. And from that, you can reconstitute whether
or not it is liked or not liked, whether it's a pleasant, whether people find it pleasant or unpleasant.
So it doesn't come out of nowhere. Yes, there's something about even if it's abstract,
even if it's abstract music, or if it's abstract art, there's some auditory or visual features there
that are generalizable and that can be used to evoke emotions. And the big question then is,
can we link that back? Obviously, the emotions didn't evolve in order to appreciate abstract art,
but they evolved to detect tigers and bears and other things. Well, are there similar kinds of visual
features? Presumably there are. So there's some visual features in the real world that for which
particular emotions evolved that can also then find a place again in abstract art and evoke similar
emotions. That's the basic story. But the answer to your question is, yes, even for these very uniquely
human sort of abstract kinds of stimuli, people have done work and found particular features in those
stimuli that will trigger emotion states in humans. And they're great stimuli to use.
Talk a little bit about hardwiring versus learned emotional states at the brain level. We know
there are brain areas that process faces, just the organization of two dots and a vertical line and
a horizontal line below it. There are neurons that like that organization of features. And I should know
the answer to the next question, but I don't. Are there neurons that are tuned to a smiling face versus
a frowning face at the level of like almost like very sparse emoji-like level? We call them units in
the brain. Are there units that are tuned to frowning faces or smiling faces? And of course,
you'd love to be able to do the experiment in somebody who had never been exposed to them for the first
time. But that's impossible to do. So I have to assume the experiment has been at least thought
about, if not done. Yeah, I mean, it's a great question. I mean, you know, with respect to face
processing in general, the sort of consensus is it's both hardwired and innate in some sense that
there's something there in the brain already at birth that's experience independent. But then it
also depends on normal maturation and development and experience. And so people like Rebecca Sachs
at MIT, for instance, has done functional neuroimaging studies on babies and shown them faces and asked
the question, how does this pulse system develop? It's always a mixture. People tend to think in terms
of black and white. It's hardwired and innate or it's learned. Nothing is either or. It's always
both. A good example is the visual word form area. So there's regions in the brain that,
like the ones that my former Caltech colleague Doris Sow studied that are specialized for faces.
But there's also a region in the brain, typically on the left in most people, that's for recognizing
words, letters. Now that couldn't have evolved because, you know, we had a long history of brain
evolution before language, written language was ever there. So the question is, how does it come
about? It can't be hardwired or innate because there wasn't long enough evolutionary time to evolve
a region of the brain for figuring out words. But if you take a look in preverbal infants at the
connectivity of this region that's going to become specialized for processing words once the infant can
read, it's already wired up in a way to other brain regions that predisposes it to be able to do
those computations that, with experience, it can later be used in order to recognize words.
I see. So there's certain preset innate systems. Coming back to your question, smiling versus
frowning faces, there are two parts to it. The first part is, I can find you a single neuron in the
brain that responds selectively for anything you like. There's like no shortage of them. But those,
in general, those single neurons don't do anything. They aren't important to understand how the brain
works because the rest of the brain that is getting its input from all these neurons and
all the downstream processing is not like a reflex. It's not listening to only that one neuron. It's
getting input from tens of thousands of neurons. So at the population level, if we record from thousands
of neurons and we ask, from that, is there information in a thousand neurons from which the rest of the
brain listening to those thousand neurons, or we as the scientist could decode smiles versus frowns?
The answer is yes. We've done that in collaboration with Uli Ruta-Sauser and Shuo Wang and colleagues
where we can record from epilepsy patients, like what Eddie Chang does, same kind of work.
And so you have information. And of course, if you think about it, there has to be information in
the brain neurons that would distinguish frowns from smiles because you can distinguish them.
So where else would it come from? It has to be there in the brain. But it's not there mechanistically
at the level of single neurons. They're very noisy. They typically respond to many different types of cues.
So you always have to think about hundreds or thousands, a large ensemble of neurons,
because that's really the kind of unit of relevant information, because that's what the rest of the
brain listens to. Yeah. I was thinking about how, you know, in a hierarchical system like the visual
system, like we have neurons that are tuned to circles, more or less, you know, center surround.
We talk about the circles, then bars, then oriented bars of a particular angle, then moving bars,
et cetera, et cetera. And so built up from simple stuff to more complex stuff. So you can build feature
detectors for lots of different things. I guess I was wondering when we come into the world,
are there cells in the fusiform area that not just like faces, but that are prepared to respond to
two dots, the eyes, a vertical thing, the nose, and then a bar that is either,
you know, bent up at the edges or bent down at the edges. And then we build on that scaffold.
I don't know that anyone's done these experiments.
Not that exact experiment, but I think that in broad strokes, the answer would be
that at birth, it's, it's crude, and it becomes more, much more refined and more granular through
experience. And then indeed, exactly what you said happens, you know, and then coming back to emotions,
if you think about, so how does the state of fear come about in the brain from seeing the,
seeing the bear or the, or the tiger? Well, at the level of the retina, it's just a bunch of pixels.
It's some, you know, blobby black shape that is looming and coming closer, et cetera. But then
progressively, you have to construct more and more abstract representations. And you well know how this
works in the visual system and artificial systems, deep convolutional neural networks that do object
classification do exactly that. They take just, you know, pixel-wise input, but then build something
abstract. Like right now, I recognize Andrew Huberman there. If I look over here, you know,
I can still recognize you. Whether you're on the left or the right, whether you're close or far away,
that would be able to recognize you invariantly with respect to those details, even though
at the level of the retina, like, like a camera taking a picture, the detailed pixels can be vastly
different. You can be left or right or close or lit in different ways. And you need to abstract from
that an invariant representation, regardless of the details. Same thing for emotions, regardless of
whether it's a bear or a tiger or a big arm pickup truck coming at you or lots of other kinds of
stimuli, they all need to funnel in to a central abstract representation. That's another key feature
of emotions. They require abstraction. And that's what makes them so flexible. And that's where you
can get David Anderson and I described it in our book as this sort of fan-in, fan-out architecture.
I can get to the emotion state from seeing a bear or smelling a bear or hearing a bear or hearing a
twig snap, hearing somebody yell, there's a bear. Zillions of different inputs, completely unlike
the rigid reflex, which only has one input. And that's it. You get the central state of fear.
And then the outputs are also diverse. I can hide, I can run away, I can defend myself. And so that
flexibility that the central emotion state affords, you can get to it in many different ways, because many
different sensory cues are informative about a potential threat. And then you can behave in very
flexible ways that are context-dependent. That's exactly what emotions allow you to do and what makes
them so different from reflexes. Reflexes is just a single path through. There's only one way to trigger it,
and there's only one behavior. So if you had only those, you would have to have a separate reflex for
the bear and for the tiger and for every possible, you know, large threat out there, which you couldn't
possibly have. It's not efficient. Yeah, the fan in, fan out visual is very,
very useful. And it gets to the next topic I'd like to ask you about, which is building social
intelligence and emotional intelligence, because we define that different ways. People who seem
unable to read the room, so to speak, versus people who are hypersensitive to other people's emotions,
not necessarily responding to them, but they're really in tune. I'll go out on a limb and say that
some of the happiest, most functional, and when I say functional, I also include in that,
they take great care of the people around them, their families, their coworkers,
people that I know and have observed are not super emotionally in tune with the emotions of others,
meaning it doesn't seem like they're clocking every little nuance. And some of the more,
I'm generalizing here, less functional, more labile. People that I've known are really in tune
with what everyone in the room is feeling, who did this, who didn't do that. And going back to our
earlier conversation, that so much of how we gauge other people's emotions is an integration over,
you know, how often they tend to acknowledge us when we walk down the hall. If the first time I met
you, you walked right by me, which who knows what would have happened, and the second time and the
third time, and then the fourth time, you say, good morning. I'd say, oh, this is a really delightful
person. If you did the opposite, said, hello, hello, hello, three days in a row, and then the fourth time,
I'd probably think like, that's weird, you know. So there's some advantage, actually, to not being
in tune with all the subtle cues of everyone around us. What in the brain is known about social
awareness, about reading the room? We talk it up these days, because indeed, empathy is important,
but this is a tricky one. I'm going to get some heat for saying this, but it's also a lot to be said
for like walking into a room, acknowledging, okay, great, and then like getting your work done.
You're trapped up into people's emotional states, because unnecessarily, because they're
labile. They're all over the place. There's a cost. Well, I think it's extremely heterogeneous,
and so this is not sort of one size fits all, and there's not one type of sort of emotional
intelligence skill that fits all occasions, and many different kinds can work. They depend on
the context. It depends on the circumstances. Initially, when James Gross had emotion regulation,
it was sort of focused on some basic mechanisms like suppression, reappraisal, acceptance,
and now the big two topics on emotional regulation are variability and flexibility. So there's not
just one way, but you need to be able to have many, many different options, and you can vary,
vary your emotional regulation responses. But the other big part of emotional regulation,
which is obvious, once you think about it, any parent would think about it, is it's interpersonal.
It's between people. You regulate other people's emotions, and you have to pick up on other people's
emotions, and you influence other people's emotions. It's a bi-directional interaction. And so I think a big
part of emotional intelligence comes from being able to read that probably in a fairly automatic way,
and in a context dependent way. And depending on the context, it can be the case that what's most
adaptive is if you really get involved with other people, and you really talk to them a lot, you're
very empathic, or you just take over. And that can work too, depending on the circumstances. So
there are multiple strategies. And I think for any of these social intelligence, emotional regulation,
any of these sort of metacognitive skills, the most successful skill is if you don't just have one,
but you have variety. And you can switch between them, and you can use context to switch between
those. Just like physiological heart rate variability, you don't want to train to just be able to have
a low heart rate, you want to be able to train to have a variable, a big range. Same thing with
emotions. What's most adaptive is being able to have a big range of emotions, and being able to switch
adaptively depending on the context between them. And I think that's where, you know, real long-term
context-dependent social intelligence for people that really come out ahead. It's not
one tiny slice where they do well and don't do well in lots of other circumstances. It's the ability
to be really adaptive and flexible and switch around. Which requires a keen sense of oneself,
like where we are in our internal state, and a keen sense of context. In fact, I observed a really
impressive physician recently, like moving through the hospital environment. I mean, he was just like all
agency. But then with the patient, it was as if he dropped into a bubble. The patient was
understandably a little nervous about what was to come, and it was remarkable. I was like,
okay, that is superb bedside manner. But then it comes time to do the actual work, and that's not
a time for emotion. It's just like 100%. You have to be able to switch.
100%. I mean, the life and well-being of the patient relies on being absolutely focused on
the task at hand. I mean, it's related, again, to the presumptive association between emotional
granularity, what Lisa Foreman Barrett pioneered decades ago, the ability to differentiate and be
aware of all the variety of emotions in you, and emotion regulation flexibility. That you're able to
adopt many different emotion regulation strategies, but in order to do so, you need the emotional
granularity to be able to be aware of all the different emotions that are going on in the first
place. It's pretty two things. One is an ability to differentiate at a very fine grain, and the other
one is to step back and have some kind of metacognitive oversight and control. So you can say, okay,
here's this full spectrum of things I could do, and you can take a look at all of those,
incorporate the context, and pick one path amongst many that you could take that's the most adaptive.
It's interesting. Some of my favorite scientists are very emotive people, and then some of my favorite
scientists, thinking of one in particular, when I was down at UC San Diego, when my lab was there,
most people probably label as a little bit on the spectrum. I won't mention his name. He would walk
into a faculty meeting where someone else was presenting, and he would say out loud to me,
like sitting there, like, is this any good? I have encountered people like that, too.
It's very disconcerting when you're giving the talk. It's disconcerting when you're giving
the talk. But I was going to say, there's also something incredibly refreshing about it,
because it's almost like they're asking the question that they need to ask. You're a little
embarrassed for them, but it's liberating. You feel like, ah, we've broken the social mold here
a little bit. And someone would say, excuse me, so-and-so, so-and-so is presenting and be like,
oh, sorry. And then we'll just sit down and then listen. I mean, they're entirely polite,
very actively engaged in the conversation. But I sometimes wish, like, how cool would that be?
Like, I'm sure there's a cost, other areas in life, but how cool would that be? You lose,
this person has a little bit less context-dependent, you know, flexibility around emotions.
And I have to imagine that they move through life in a way that's kind of like liberated.
Well, they wouldn't have this huge cognitive load all the time.
Right. And he's extremely smart. Now that's qualitative, right? But like incredible,
actually a physicist turned neuroscientist. And I just thought, man, that's pretty cool.
And then the more you go into engineering and science fields, the more of these people you
encounter. This is true. You see fewer of these people in the performing arts, for instance.
Sure. My lab studies autism, amongst other things. And you certainly would have the case that as a
spectrum, yes, indeed, you would have mathematicians, engineers, lots of people who are very successful,
who are on the spectrum to some extent. And I think, you know, coming back to what you were saying,
it's sort of liberating or simplifying. If you had to really effortfully cognitively think about
how to regulate your social behavior and make all the right moves and not offend anybody, you were
worried about that all the time. It would be overwhelming. And I think it is overwhelming
for many people with autism, that you need to somehow internalize it. And it has to be
relatively effortless and automatic. It has to become automatic at some level. And then you can move
for life fairly smoothly in a socially very complex way. And that's what's difficult for many people
with autism, that they lack that part. They can compensate to some extent, but the cognitive load
starts really being an impediment. Because if you have to track everything, you have to remember,
okay, I should make eye contact. I have to remember turn-taking. If you have to cognitively remember
all those things, it's just overwhelming. So you have to be able to somehow have it be
automatic at some level. I'd like to take a quick break and acknowledge one of our sponsors,
Element. Element is an electrolyte drink that has everything you need and nothing you don't.
That means the electrolytes, sodium, magnesium, and potassium all in the correct ratios,
but no sugar. Proper hydration is critical for brain and body function. Even a slight degree
of dehydration can diminish your cognitive and physical performance. It's also important that
you get adequate electrolytes. The electrolytes, sodium, magnesium, and potassium are vital for
the functioning of all cells in your body, especially your neurons or your nerve cells.
Drinking Element makes it very easy to ensure that you're getting adequate hydration
and adequate electrolytes. My days tend to start really fast, meaning I have to jump right into
work or right into exercise. So to make sure that I'm hydrated and I have sufficient electrolytes,
when I first wake up in the morning, I drink 16 to 32 ounces of water with an Element packet
dissolved in it. I also drink Element dissolved in water during any kind of physical exercise that
I'm doing, especially on hot days when I'm sweating a lot and losing water and electrolytes.
Element has a bunch of great tasting flavors. In fact, I love them all. I love the watermelon,
the raspberry, the citrus, and I really love the lemonade flavor. So if you'd like to try Element,
you can go to drinkelement.com slash Huberman to claim a free Element sample pack with any purchase.
Again, that's drinkelement.com slash Huberman to claim a free sample pack.
Let's talk about autism. And I'll just put the mention up front because this is a topic that
sometimes gets people triggered. Let's leave out for the time being, not because it isn't important,
it is important. Let's leave out severe cases of autism where people need lifelong care. They can't
care for themselves. And let's talk about the rest of the spectrum. Already in that statement, I'm sure
I violated some of the newer nomenclature, but let's just liberate ourselves a little bit,
come at this from a place of benevolence and trying to understand social dynamics, social processing in
the brain. So we're not talking about people with severe stereotypies who just need lifelong care,
even, et cetera. We're talking about the rest of the category. So something like this former colleague
of mine in San Diego. A little bit on the spectrum. For all I know, he's been one of our
participants in some of our studies. Maybe. And he's a delightful person, happy marriage,
happy family. Everyone in his lab adored him and brilliant scientist. And by my read,
highly functional in all aspects of life, but definitely not tuned in to what other people
are thinking or doing. And context mattered, right? I mean, he understood what not to do in a
broad sense, but, you know, he was free of this burden that you described. So there's a lot of
emphasis nowadays on kids who have autism of the sort that we're describing and the need we're told
to train them to make eye contact and read faces. So this lands square in your work. Maybe you could
just fill out a bit of what's now known, what's thought, what's not known. It's a great topic. I mean,
the way that I personally have approached it is not with a primary interest in autism. I don't have a
family member who has autism. I'm not, you don't have any personal experience. It's really been,
just like with the amygdala lesion patient, it's the, my main motivation has been to just understand
the mind, cognition, emotion in general, and with respect to autism, by understanding individual
differences. Everybody's different from everybody else. And autism is one particular dimension that we
just have a lot of tools to look at. That is, you know, social interaction, social awareness,
ability to read other people's emotions. And so that dimension of social variability
maps onto one of the facets of autism spectrum disorder. And so that's why
we've looked at both people who do not have any diagnosis of autism. There's still,
there's a range of autistic like traits that you can quantify with questionnaires that are well
regarded. And then once you get to a DSM-5 diagnosis, you have more and more severe cases
of autism with respect to social functioning that again, you can quantify using tools like the ADOS,
etc. But it's a spectrum that I personally look at as a particularly interesting and important
dimension of individual differences in social interactions. And other people in my lab
that have different motivations, they have family members with autism, for instance,
so they're personally interested in autism as a psychiatric category.
But coming to your question, there's a lot of really interesting work and a lot of opportunities
now that we've been actually using in our lab as well to look at the question of processing about
faces, eye contact, etc. I mean, right now, how much eye contact are you making with me? How much eye
contact am I making with you? It is extremely variable. I mean, the eyes move around, they carry a lot of
information. You know, socially, there's a gigantic range there. It's data that are now fairly easy to
quantify and collect in hundreds or thousands of people using their webcams. And so we have a study
going on where people watch, for example, a Zoom video, other people interacting, talking, and we use
the webcam on their laptop to record where they are looking on the screen when they have that Zoom video
going on. So we can quantify across large numbers of people. And the basic finding has been
that people who are further along have high score higher on this dimension of the autism spectrum of
social interaction with just questionnaire based measures, or a psychiatric diagnosis, make less eye
contact, and as well as other features. So we're looking at contact with the person who's talking,
distraction to other things. We have experimental features where there's a person talking, they're
making eye contact, there's like TV or something that goes on in the background, and we can quantify
to what extent is your visual attention, your gaze that we can quantify from the webcam,
captured by somebody looking, somebody talking, somebody smiling or laughing, the TV going on in the
background as a distractor. And we can put all of that into a big model and ask what is it that normally
drives visual attention? And what is it that distinguishes people with autism and where they
would look? And the basic answer is that the social features like eyes or who's talking have less of a
weight on where autistic people would look than the distractors, but they tend to be more distracted.
And that that is, we've been doing the study every month now for a year, that seems to be a temporally
stable personality traits like feature of autism spectrum disorder. So it fluctuates to some extent,
and we're trying to quantify, does it interact with whether you've slept badly the night before,
or you're stressed, or other things that can change, those do have an effect. But the answer seems to be
it's fairly temporally stable, and it's almost like a signature for individuals. So there's some people
that are real face lookers, and they look at faces a lot. And there's some people that look at faces
hardly at all. And that seems to be stable across time, and like a basic personality trait.
In this population of people diagnosed? Across the board, for everybody.
I see. If I just take the general population,
on average, it's the case that those people who have a diagnosis of autism or who score higher
on autistic traits, even if they don't have a diagnosis, look less at faces. But across everybody,
it's the case that some people look a lot at faces, some people don't, and that that's temporally
stable. So in general, right now, if you quantify it from this podcast, how often do I make eye
contact or look at you? And then you ask, you know, like in the classroom or in the lab meeting,
how often do I make eye contact? It would be similar proportion that I'm just like not a face
looker or eye looker, and you might be, it's like a stable personality trait. And it's associated
coarsely with this dimension in autism spectrum disorder. But of course, the million dollar
question is, what else is it associated with? Is it predictive of career success? Is it predictive
of anything else? And so we don't know, we're measuring everything else and getting lots of
questionnaires on these people to ask, what are the associations? And is there any causal hypothesis
that we would come up with that? If you don't look at faces a lot, there's some consequences. If you
look at faces a lot, there are other consequences. If that were the case, we're not there yet,
that would make very interesting predictions, which may well, maybe I should be looking at
your face all the time, and the podcast would get a million hits, or who knows what.
Just be you, as we say. Well, that's, I mean, that's another big question, which we're looking
at these longitudinal studies, which is a question of, to what extent can you change who you are?
And you know, you're emo, we were talking about emotion regulation, you can regulate your emotions,
you can have this metacognitive insight, you can have some control. Can you change if you're
extrovert or neurotic? Can you change your personality? And the answer seems to be to some
extent, for some variables more than others, but we're trying to quantify that. So we have this big
longitudinal data set where we give people tons and tons of questionnaires about their personality,
about their mood, about lots of things, and are asking to what extent over time do they get pushed
around and that can change, and which ones stay constant and constitutes of the core of their
personality that's unchangeable. But I think it's a super, super interesting question. What parts of
you can change and what parts of you cannot? Yeah, I think about this all the time. I feel like some
people, this is pseudoscientific, what I'm about to describe, they seem to have very high autonomic,
what I call like RPM. I have a, it's more of a former colleague, because I haven't been working
in that field for a while. But if you ever see Botton Rosca from Basel, give a talk,
like he moves a lot. He's very electric. He's also very thin. He moves in his brain. He's exceedingly
smart. But he has a high basal metabolic rate. High basal metabolic rate. Like a hummingbird.
Yeah, but he moves a lot, right? Right, right. And then other people, they move less. I think about
this all the time, because I'm fascinated by and I love dogs. I go to this AKC meet the breeds thing every
year. I don't go every year, they do it every year. But I highly recommend people go,
even if you don't want a dog, because you get to see all the different genetic variation,
which of course relates to body size, but also temperament. And if you just look at them.
Bulldogs are probably more on the slow, mellow side compared to Yorkshire Terriers that are more.
Very little spontaneous movement. I think it's one of the reasons why people feel comfortable
approaching a bulldog. Whereas like a, you know, pit bulls are always kind of like winding around and
moving. But some dogs, it may relate to other things, cuteness and whatnot. But some people just seem
to have a lot of spontaneous movement. Other people are more stable in their bodily movements.
And it does seem to relate to kind of how excitable they are or not excitable they are. So you can
imagine like if you're, if you're humming at a higher RPM, you can like more prone to action or
speech. But it's a super interesting observation, because the question of course, is to what extent
does it relate to how their mind is working, right? I mean, as we're talking now, and as you were just
talking, you know, we're moving our hands, we're moving our body, we're moving our face.
You know, we're not just sitting there speaking. So to some extent, all of these bodily movements
are interfaced with thought. If I had to sit completely still and not, you know, move,
it would be pretty hard to have this conversation, right? So to some extent, bodily movements actually
help us structure our thoughts. It's not just like a large language model. It's not just language going
on. It interfaces with the body. And it punctuates thoughts to some extent. So I think it's super
interesting. And it's certainly the case that the way that somebody moves their body does say
something about how they're thinking as well. Yeah, I've been reading my audio book. And I asked
them, the sound technicians to allow me to stand while I read it. Much easier to read an audio book
and to put inflection, you actually can lean in when you want to emphasize something. And you can,
you know, point to the words for a moment. But then when you need to work through a passage that
needs to be very finely structured with little emotion, because that happens too, if you clasp your hands
and do it. So our friend, Eddie Chang tells me that the hand representations in the brain are very
close to the language center. So these were probably our first tools of language, or at least they
co-evolved. Well, your mouth and your hands are the most dexterous and overrepresented in the brain.
Right. You can, you know, control the world with them and you can move from the most.
Yeah. When, you know, when the COVID pandemic started 2020, we weren't allowed to go on campus at
all. So we sat around in our apartments. I sat at home. We had lab meetings on zoom, only zoom and
lectures. All the classes were on zoom prior to that. And then zoom took off and now it's most
meetings are hybrid. But before that point, everything was face to face. I would stand up
and lecture. We would talk face to face and suddenly switching to just seeing a bunch of
often little, just black squares, right? For the, for the whole classroom there on zoom.
That was a hard switch, that lack of an interactive nature, which is something that we're looking at
now. I think it's going to be super cool. I have a graduate student just starting this.
The experiment is this, I would see your face on a screen. And that's it. I would see a video of
you. I would zoom with you right now. And we could be having this podcast over zoom. I actually thought
we were going to have this over zoom. So I'm very happy. It's not over zoom.
Always better in person.
And then you're here in person, right? And it feels different. It feels different. And so
we're sort of trying to parameterize that degree of social realness of social interaction. And then
we're doing that with people with autism asking, where does it change? And how difficult is it for
people with autism to interact with another person? Is it equally difficult over zoom? Is it equally
difficult over zoom? If you have the selfie camera turned off, the other person can't see you and you
know that. And so we're trying to look at the degree of actual social interaction as a relevant
dimension. And I think it makes a huge difference. I mean, it feels completely different
being face to face, but if you're on zoom, let alone if I just watch a video, that's not
actually aligned time. The way I described the kind of higher or lower RPM before, but perhaps
made it sound like one or the other was better. But I think sometimes about like Alex Honnold,
who again, who was a guest on this podcast, and there being claims that his amygdala doesn't react as
much. Anyway, we could, we could talk about that. I think Alex kind of like maybe chuckles a little bit
at those studies because he does experience anxiety and fear, just not in the context of this, like,
highly trained situation he's put himself in every single day for so long. But I do have to wonder
whether people who go out on long runs, for instance, there's not a lot of talking going on,
or Alex, he's devoting his physical and mental energetic resources toward climbing and figuring out
these how to navigate high risk, high consequence.
I mean, there you're probably just in flow. You're just like totally absorbed in what you're
doing. If you're doing Alex Honnold type climbing.
Once he's got it, but like to work out the puzzle of like with ropes first of how to maneuver
so that he can actually free solo it is, is a remarkable thing. But I almost get the impression
that if people speak less, that they're able to devote more mental and physical resources to the
thing they're doing. I never ran ultras, but I recall like running, you know, I used to run like a
long eight to 10 mile run on Sundays used to be a thing. Now it's getting shorter and shorter run.
I have to go get it back, but come back from those. And there's a fatigue component that confounds what I'm
about to say, but one is a lot less reactive when you spent a bunch of time just in your own head
and you've learned to tolerate the voice in your own head. I find that I'm much calmer after I've
spent a bunch of time alone because I've gone through that kind of initial stage of the mind
fluttering. And then you want to communicate with people and I'll lock up my phone in a box these days
to do real work. And I come out of it and things come my way and they're sort of out there and over
there. And unless they really demand my attention, they kind of just don't grab me. Whereas I think
when we're highly engaged in our own mental dialogue, it's almost like we're trying to
converse with the world. So I think there's real value to doing these solo treks and to devoting
time to getting past that need to engage with the world. I think it's very, very useful.
Yeah. I mean, I'm sure it's idiosyncratic. It'll vary. But I think
that particular aspect that you mentioned that you can just be comfortable in your own mind
and that that's beneficial, I think that's a big part. It's a big part of lots of training
techniques and big part of lots of meditative techniques that you just, but again, it's very
individual. It's not just sort of one size fits all, but the ability to not just be driven by sensory
input and be comfortable with your own mind. It's not like you're doing nothing at all. You're training.
You're training your own mind to be comfortable. And I think the consequence of that is then
subsequently, when you encounter challenges in the world, you're actually better equipped
to deal with those and better equipped to regulate your emotion. But when you're just at peace with
yourself, if you're not doing nothing, your brain is being trained all the time and it's being
trained in a useful way. And I think the ability to detach and decouple from the constant challenges and
sensory information that's normally coming in is like sleep allows the brain to actually train
itself and focus on particular internal regulation strategies that are then subsequently useful for
dealing with the world later. Could we say that one form of potentially useful emotional intelligence
or social intelligence training is to just spend some time in your own head, either moving or not
moving. You could do it meditating or you could do it running, but to just resist the temptation to get
pulled out into the world and just get good at just sitting with these things that we call emotions and
thoughts. I think so, especially it's again, it's going to be individual and it's going to vary,
but I think so, especially if you can get some kind of metacognitive or reflective awareness and work
on what is going on in your mind. And ultimately, it's training control. It's training control of your
emotions and training control of your thoughts. And if you're constantly bombarded and just dealing with
other stuff coming in, you don't have time to do that. It's called social media. Exactly. Yes. Of
which I have none. And so if you're just by yourself, you know, if you're running or if you're
meditating or if you're trained up, if you're in an ice bath, I think you actually get a particular type
of internal training that you just don't have the leisure to get if you're bombarded by social media,
for instance. Yes. You know, every beginning of my lab meeting, now people have their laptops open and
their phones out. We put them down and we actually have five minutes of silence, a sort of meditative
silence for people to clear their minds. Really? Yeah. Five minutes or three minutes at the beginning
of every lab meeting, we have a short meditative session. I put a picture up of some beautiful beach
on the north shore of Kauai in case people want to look at that. But many people just close their eyes.
People can do whatever they want. But the idea is to clear your mind and focus and relax and get into
a frame of mind where you're actually now most receptive to listen to the research presentation
that's coming up. Because, you know, you come in and your mind is all over the place and, you know,
there's an email here and the phone is going and you're just, your mind is buzzing. So quieting that,
finding some focus and then being able to engage subsequently much better with the real world,
listening to the talk. I think that's, that helps. And we do that every lab meeting,
Mondays at noon seems to work for people. How long have you implemented this?
We started it in 2020 when George Floyd was killed, specifically to remember George Floyd. So it was,
there was a very specific starting point because many people were upset and we figured
we needed some kind of remembrance or just a moment of silence to acknowledge things. And then it morphed
into, you know, you can remember whatever you like, you can just relax. And then it sort of morphed
into this idea, well, you know, let's just have a moment of silence and just like recalibrate from the
busy world and everything that's just been going on to now, you know, I mean, it's good to do on average
every day in any case, but certainly right now before we launch into the research presentation at a lab
meetings are sort of morphed from a moment of silence to remember somebody to a short meditation
essentially. I love it. My neuroscience colleagues are doing ice baths, training for a hundred mile
races and doing, um, the question is, is it helping by, am I getting more nature papers as a consequence
of any of these? That's a different metric. That's a different metric. Uh, you seem like a happy,
vital person. I'm happy. And you're writing books and you're doing public education here. In addition to
all of that, I'd like to actually stay on this meditation thing for a moment. Rick Rubin,
famed music producer came on this podcast. He also happens to be a friend of mine. And right as we
sat down, he said, um, can we do some coherence breathing first? He plays, it's like a tone.
You do some inhale, exhale. And you know, he, he likes these transition. Breathing exercises are great.
Yeah. These transition tools and they will increase your heart rate variability and these kinds of things.
Right. But I think that one of the most interesting and understudied things in our field is task
switching, whether it's emotional tasks, switching or cognitive tasks, switching, like we assume the
brain operates in step functions. Like, oh, I'm out on the street. I navigate traffic. I park my car
and I come in and I podcast. And what you're doing at the beginning of this lab meeting in on the one
hand is a meditation, but it it's, you're pivoting the brain circuits toward what comes next.
Yeah. I don't think we talk enough as neuroscientists about the fact that the brain doesn't just
immediately switch over, that you're carrying residual activity from whatever you were doing
before. Yes. Yes. There's a cost to that, a well-known cost. So as soon as you switch into something,
there's a cost carried over from the previous task and you're much slower and it's more difficult
for the couple of next trials on the new task. So there's always a switching cost, which shows you
that switching is hard and some, for some reason, and there's a couple of theories for why it should
be hard. There's some residue, some sort of inertia being carried over previously. There's some
reconfiguration in the brain required between what you were doing in the previous task and the new task,
but all of those would seem to require some effort. And it's definitely a skill and something that
people are looking at a lot in brain recordings in humans and thinking a lot about how to design into AI,
that ability to switch quickly and knowing how to switch, anticipating when to switch,
is a hugely important skill. And we don't teach it. Like here we are talking about emotional
intelligence, social awareness, and these kinds of things. And I think most people think, oh,
we should sit down and look at a bunch of faces and learn to detect the subtle cues in faces, or
we should make more eye contact. And what I'm hearing today is while some of that might be true,
most things are pointing in a different direction. We had a guest on this podcast, DJ Shipley, who's a former
tier one SEAL team operator. That's another high risk, high consequence world, but then he's out
now, he's no longer deploying. And he talked about his routine for coming home. It's like,
he knows he's rehearsing as he comes out of the car, just like as if it were an op, you know,
I'm going to hit the door. My daughter's going to come running from this direction. My other daughter's
going to come in, Patsy's going to be in the kitchen, but he's rehearsed it and he knows exactly
where he'll set his bag so he can scoop his daughter up. Yeah.
People either chuckled or I think we're kind of taken aback by that until he said, but this is the
way that I know I can drop everything from the day and be at my best when I enter that environment.
And you know, this is the kind of a quote unquote, like hyper Y chromosome version of kind of home and
family life. But it was remarkable what the comments, when we ran this clip on social media,
the men were all kind of like, you know, like you have a system, dude, and you follow it. And the
women were like, yes, fantastic. Like this is somebody who's prioritizing how he shows up. He's
leaving everything else outside, which is a kind of, you know, it's a more of a 1950s version of that.
That skill, being able to switch is super, super important. It was super important.
And it's trainable. It's largely trainable. And I think if you have meditative exercises,
they train exactly that. It's a huge switch, right? You're switching from like constantly being
bombarded and dealing with stuff in the world, to suddenly putting all of that aside and just being
inside. And, and it has health benefits, you know, Richie Davidson, for instance, I don't know if you
have. Yeah, we had him here. You know, he studied Tibetan monks and long term meditators who've
meditated 10,000 hours or whatever, which we can't afford to do. But he has a lot of studies on,
even for the rest of us, you know, short stretches of meditation, regular meditative exercises, you know,
these done well controlled studies have demonstrable health benefits for sure. So again,
it comes back to this issue of variability, being able to switch and having lots of variability and
training that is definitely beneficial. It's beneficial for just basic physiology is beneficial
for emotion granularity and emotion regulation. It's beneficial for control of thought is when
you're being externally oriented versus meditating. All of those are, to a large extent, trainable
skills in variability and, and control. So the experiment I'd love to see done,
maybe your lab will do this would be what is the cost of tasks switching if you do or do not
insert this five minutes of silence, like because you're spending five minutes, and we know the
transition is choppy into the next thing that you're doing. So there's some overlap there. But by
introducing the period of silence, you reduce the amount of time in order to switch your brain over
to this new mode. Presumably, you're seeing positive effects in these lab meetings of doing it.
Yeah, we should, we should do a study, it would be, you know, we would have to think about the
right controls. We are looking at task switching, actually, in these brain recordings in epilepsy
patients, we're looking at single unit recordings and how those representations change when you switch
between tasks. It's a great study, we're just working up the analyses now. But we don't have the
intervention that you were just speaking about. So we don't have half the patients are getting
meditative training and half are not. But the extent to which an intervention like that can
improve your ability to switch or some other concrete metric. I think that's, yes, those are
exactly the types of studies that should be done. I think Richie is probably doing studies like that.
They did a study of five minutes of meditation per day and showed that people experienced tremendous
increases in anxiety during the initial phase of the study, like just having to sit there with your
thoughts and let everything stir. I actually think of short meditations like that, at least initially,
as another version of the ice bath. Well, it is. And I think when we started,
and you know, we have new summer students coming on nuclear in the lab and say, okay, I don't usually
say too much. Okay, we're going to just like, like three minutes of silence and everybody's like
this. And these summer students are looking around, but what's going on? It's very stressful,
right? And if you just tell them, well, just like, don't do anything. I mean,
this is obviously extremely difficult for young children. Don't do anything,
right? Just be completely silent and quiet for one minute or five minutes. It is hard to inhibit
behavior. It's really hard to do, but it's trainable. It's completely trainable. And a big
part of it, you know, we're in this same conference room that David Anderson has his lab
meetings in, which is where I can always see that he goes on for hours and hours. It has glass walls.
And so people are walking around outside, looking at us sitting there in silence,
pretty wondering, not much progress being done in that lab meeting. So there's that whole social
perception aspect. But again, once you get over that and get used to it, it's very easy to do
these exercises. And it's definitely a trainable skill for sure. Yeah, we were on the East Coast
in Annapolis at the Naval Academy. These are very accomplished students, almost 4,000 of them. And one
of the most incredible things about that environment is everyone goes into the cafeteria for lunch
and all of a sudden the bell sounds and you could hear a pin drop. But there's thousands of people
around you. You hear a bell again, the meal begins. Walking into the auditorium, it's shuffle,
shuffle, shuffle, talking, talking, talking, talking, talking. Boom. It's a step function. They're
training this in themselves. And the other thing, no phones. No one has phones during the day. I think
they get an hour where they can access their phones. I normally, my phone, it's on right now
because you guys wanted to text me. But normally my phone is off or I don't have a phone on me.
And zero social media, not on Facebook, I'm not on Instagram, zero. I just, you know, whenever
people ask me, they say, oh, you know, can I hook you up with, what's that thing? LinkedIn or whatever.
I'm not on LinkedIn. I don't care what LinkedIn is. They're always surprised and they say, well,
why are you not on the social media? And I say, why would I be? I'm already above 100%
in terms of people emailing me. I don't need more. So I'm, yeah, zero.
Love that you've given yourself permission to do that. I put social media on a separate phone
so that I can really track my time on there. And I just use it only to post,
read a little bit, and then I'm out. I just, I can't take the mental noise.
Before we started recording, you mentioned that you fortunately successfully overcame a
bout of illness. Yes.
I'm curious whether the process of going through that, the diagnosis, the treatment,
and then emerging from it, thank goodness, healthy, had you at times thinking about the
science of emotions. I mean, that's an emotional experience to say the least. You don't have to
share with us exactly what it was, but were there times when what your knowledge of the brain's
ability to process emotions for better or worse was a useful tool to you in that context?
I guess so. I mean, you know, only in the most indirect sense, but I guess it's about emotion
regulation. Well, it's got two things. I think it's about emotion regulation. So, you know,
initially when you get a diagnosis that reminds you of your mortality, it's sort of a mixture of,
you know, fear, sadness, worry, you know, all these negative emotions. And so you're
regulating that and it's interpersonal for sure. So interpersonal emotion regulation between me and
my wife, us talking about it. So that's like a huge part of the process. You're not regulating
those negative emotions anymore, but you're buying into, you're getting more other emotions like awe,
gratitude, acceptance, all of these emotions we were talking about before that I think are largely
uniquely human that really makes you appreciate and be just grateful for what you have. So that whole
process of regulating the sort of, you know, immediate stressors and then coming to having
more gratitude and awe in everyday life. And then, you know, also, I mean, I think one big consequence
of anything like that is that you have this metacognitive perspective on your lifeline and,
you know, where you are, how much time you have left, and how to value that and what to do and
what to plan and how to allocate your time to things that are worthwhile. And so in my case,
one of those components was, you know, signing up for this 100-mile ultra marathon, starting to train
for it, and then just pushing through all of that. So, you know, one of the consequences of the therapy
for this was I had lots of joint pain and lots of fatigue. So I tell my doctor about that,
you say, that's great. That means it's working. It's just like, yes, but the side effects are
preventing me from training for a 100-mile race. And so pushing through that, I think it just,
it makes you grateful for what you have and makes you just be in awe of the fact that, you know,
we were briefly talking about consciousness before, that there's a world there at all. You tend to have
this perspective that physics gives us of the way the world works, that, you know, the world is going on,
and when you die, you get plucked out of that, and everything else goes on. But from a neuroscience
perspective, it's kind of the opposite. You get the sense that the whole world is actually a construction
of stuff in your brain. And as you get older, little things drop out, and various people die,
and you're unable to do things, and eventually, you lose the whole world. So rather than thinking of
death, as we normally do, as the world loses you, the neuroscience perspective is the inverse,
which is you lose the world. So you have like, you know, a couple of decades left, and then you're
going to lose everything. And that's coming. So live it up. I love it. And thank you so much for being
willing to answer that question. Throughout today's conversation, I'm struck by the fact that your work
plays such a prominent role in your life and your life and your work, even if we weren't necessarily
connecting the dots in that way, that the fact that you do practices specifically to tap into your
autonomic nervous system, emotion regulation, and at the same time, the fact that you look at neural
circuits and do extremely well-controlled studies to explore the mechanics that translate to everybody.
Like, this is a, in case anyone hasn't told you, and because I sit at a unique vantage point, both
having done academic research and now in public health communication, people need to hear this
and see and experience scientists like you. So thank you so much for coming here today, for being willing
to open up about some of this, and frankly, for doing the work that you do for so many years and such
at such a high level. And I'm so grateful that you're writing yet another book. If it's not out yet,
we can't put a link to it just yet, but when it comes out, I'll surely get a copy. And even though
you're not on social media, I'll be sure to talk about it after I've read it, because as I did the
prior book that you wrote with David. Thank you very much, Andrew. It was a pleasure being here.
We'll stay in touch, and maybe at some point I can tell you that I finished a 100-mile race,
and the book got published. Excellent. Thank you. I have no doubt that you will. Whether I join you
for that 100-mile race is a completely different story, but thank you so much, Ralph. Appreciate you.
Thanks, my pleasure. Thank you. Thank you for joining me for today's discussion with Dr. Ralph
Adolphs. To learn more about his work and to find links to his previous and forthcoming books,
please see the link in the show note caption. If you're learning from and or enjoying this podcast,
please subscribe to our YouTube channel. That's a terrific zero-cost way to support us. In addition,
please follow the podcast by clicking the follow button on both Spotify and Apple. And on both
Spotify and Apple, you can leave us up to a five-star review, and you can now leave us comments at both
Spotify and Apple. Please also check out the sponsors mentioned at the beginning and throughout
today's episode. That's the best way to support this podcast. If you have questions for me or
comments about the podcast, or guests or topics that you'd like me to consider for the Huberman
Lab podcast, please put those in the comments section on YouTube. I do read all the comments.
For those of you that haven't heard, I have a new book coming out. It's my very first book.
It's entitled Protocols, an Operating Manual for the Human Body. This is a book that I've been working on
for more than five years, and that's based on more than 30 years of research and experience. And it
covers protocols for everything from sleep to exercise to stress control, protocols related to
focus and motivation. And of course, I provide the scientific substantiation for the protocols
that are included. The book is now available by presale at protocolsbook.com. There you can find links
to various vendors. You can pick the one that you like best. Again, the book is called Protocols,
an Operating Manual for the Human Body. And if you're not already following me on social media,
I am Huberman Lab on all social media platforms. So that's Instagram, X, Threads, Facebook, and
LinkedIn. And on all those platforms, I discuss science and science-related tools, some of which
overlaps with the content of the Huberman Lab podcast, but much of which is distinct from the
information on the Huberman Lab podcast. Again, it's Huberman Lab on all social media platforms.
And if you haven't already subscribed to our Neural Network newsletter,
the Neural Network newsletter is a zero cost monthly newsletter that includes podcast summaries,
as well as what we call protocols in the form of one to three page PDFs that cover everything from
how to optimize your sleep, how to optimize dopamine, deliberate cold exposure. We have
a foundational fitness protocol that covers cardiovascular training and resistance training.
All of that is available completely zero cost. You simply go to Hubermanlab.com, go to the menu tab in
the top right corner, scroll down to newsletter and enter your email. And I should emphasize that we do not
share your email with anybody. Thank you once again for joining me for today's discussion with Dr. Ralph
Adolph Adolphs. And last, but certainly not least, thank you for your interest in science.